<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God all in all or The highest happines of the saints. Jn [sic] two parts. The I. Asserting this happiness to consist in the enjoyment of God. II. Enquiring into the quality of that enjoyment. Together with a short appendix, wherein is very briefly considered, the claim of natural reason, and private inspirations to a guidance of us in the things of God. Also what courses dishonour the Gospel, and what duties we owe it. By Edward Buckler, preacher of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Buckler, Edward, 1610-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5349</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1442_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209631</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868496</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868496</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169964</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77757)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169964)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 184:E1442[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God all in all or The highest happines of the saints. Jn [sic] two parts. The I. Asserting this happiness to consist in the enjoyment of God. II. Enquiring into the quality of that enjoyment. Together with a short appendix, wherein is very briefly considered, the claim of natural reason, and private inspirations to a guidance of us in the things of God. Also what courses dishonour the Gospel, and what duties we owe it. By Edward Buckler, preacher of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Buckler, Edward, 1610-1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 144, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Luke Fawn, at the sign of the Parrot in Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "I. Asserting .. enjoyment." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>With final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Includes a seven-page outline at end.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 10th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169964:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GOD ALL IN ALL: OR THE <hi>HIGHEST HAPPINES</hi> OF THE SAINTS.</p>
            <p>Jn two Parts.</p>
            <p>The
<list>
                  <item>I. Aſſerting this Happineſs to conſiſt in the Enjoyment of GOD.</item>
                  <item>II. Enquiring into the Quality of that Enjoyment.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a ſhort APPENDIX, wherein is very briefly conſidered, The claim of Natural Reaſon, and private Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to a guidance of us in the things of GOD. Alſo what courſes diſhonour the Goſpel, and what Duties we owe it.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD BUCKLER,</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>Whom have I in heaven but thee? and there is none upon earth that I deſire beſides thee.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 73.25.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Luke Fawn,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Parrot</hi> in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169964:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169964:2"/>
            <head>To the truly, and heartily Religious LADY, <hi>Grace Sydenham,</hi> Wife to the Right Honourable Colonel <hi>Willam Sydenham,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and one of his Highneſs's moſt honorable Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make me an object of your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding many and great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, which you could not have done, had it not been
<pb facs="tcp:169964:3"/>your principle to be good, <hi>gratis;</hi> that I might not miſs an occaſion (which I may never be able to offer my ſelf again) of putting this into a publique ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, is much of what I have to plead for ſending you theſe Papers. I had never any thing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn you but my thanks, and how much I am hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in arrear for due expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it, the leſs you do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, the more I yet owe you.</p>
            <p>The further errand of this
<pb facs="tcp:169964:3"/>diſcourſe is not to tell you where your happineſſe is: you know GOD too well to be able to miſtake in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment of that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, nor to tax you for ſeeking it where you know 'tis not; You love God too well, to ſuffer any thing in your heart to ſit above him. Have not I obſerv'd the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacie of your ſpirit, how tenderly you meddle with the Earth, from a holy jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie leſt your converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould not be enough in Heaven? But it is (Madam)
<pb facs="tcp:169964:4"/>to offer it ſelf as a poor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in the hand of a great GOD, of ſome addition to the <hi>heaven</hi> you are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in, the comforts of this here (though not the joyes of that hereafter) are capable of an augmentation. Who can tell, but that even by this means, your Communion with your God may be further'd? And if but one <hi>glimpſe</hi> the more of <hi>divine beauty</hi> ſhine in upon your ſoul, and raiſe but a <hi>rapture</hi> the more upon your ſpirit, I ſhall not be
<pb facs="tcp:169964:4"/>totally diſappointed in what J aim at: And if you ſaw my heart, you would finde it very full of wiſhes, that J were able to doe you, not better ſervice, but more of this.</p>
            <p>Many do already very well know, and J do hereby publiquely declare, That there is not that man alive, to whom J am ſo much in debt as to your Honourable Husband; and very much am I below any poſsible e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of gratitude to him, unleſſe it be of this kinde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169964:5"/>
            <p> If you ſhall ask, Why then doe I not direct this (if this be all) unto himſelf? Why! Madam, what do I elſe in directing it to you? But if this ſatisfie not, I muſt diſcover my deſign in doing it by you. It is (to confeſſe all ingenuouſly) that this naked acknowledgement, unable otherwiſe to ſignifie half enough, might be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered (by a <hi>medium</hi> of conveighance ſo extreamly well-pleaſing) ſufficiently acceptable. If I miſſe not here, though I may beg of
<pb facs="tcp:169964:5"/>you ſome other favours, you ſhall never be ſolicited to doe me a greater; and J ſhall conſtantly pray, That the Lord (your exceeding great reward) would wrap up your ſoul in the boſome of his love, give you ſo much of <hi>Himſelf,</hi> as may be had by any <hi>means,</hi> at any <hi>time,</hi> and in it a comfortable fore-taſte of what cannot be all had, till you come to enjoy him <hi>immediately</hi> for <hi>ever.</hi> Doubtleſſe I may be guilty of many failings as to other things, but this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution
<pb facs="tcp:169964:6"/>for your many favours ſhall be daily pay'd, by,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt humble, and very much obliged Servant, <hi>EDVVARD BUCKLER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169964:6"/>
            <head>To the pious Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have no intent to make an <hi>Apologie</hi> for appearing in Print; for who conſtrained me? Or to talk of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the importunitie of Friends hath had upon theſe Papers to thruſt them out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world: This were to publiſh a ſuppoſition of no very great abundance either of friendſhip or judgement, in thoſe I ſtand to in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. I have no mind to
<pb facs="tcp:169964:7"/>crave pardon for med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with ſo high and glorious a ſubject: we are doubtleſſe allowed the contemplation of what we are promiſed the fruition. Nor do <hi>I</hi> go about to excuſe my very weak and unanſwerable management of it; is any man bound to impoſsibilities? J doe not know what <hi>you</hi> will do, but <hi>God accepteth according to what a man hath.</hi> You have indeed this upon no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count than the ſence of my duty, to pay contribution to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the well-fare of the
<pb facs="tcp:169964:7"/>Saints, though out of my own Pariſh. J have taxed my ſelf to what I ought, becauſe to what J was able: If it offer any of your ſouls an occaſion of meeting your God but once the oftner, you will be no looſers; becauſe the diſcourſe is not qualified unto any probabilitie of giving you ſatisfaction, J have purpoſely choſen a ſubject that can doe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly. GOD can fill up, and content all the ſoul; whom J know you will be glad to converſe with by
<pb facs="tcp:169964:8"/>any <hi>means,</hi> though (if that were poſsible) it ſhould be leſse conſiderable than this, tendered by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your unworthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in the things of CHRIST, <hi>E.B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169964:8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. 15.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—That God may be All, in All.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>PART. I.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>Sect. I. <hi>The Text Explained.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter there be two things, which it is the Apoſtles principal deſign to make good; <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The Doctrine of the Goſpell by the Reſurrection of Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>2. The Generall Reſurrection of the dead.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The latter is proſecuted from the twelfth verſe forward, of which you have,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169964:9"/>the
<list>
                     <item>1. Confirmation by many Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</item>
                     <item>2. Order of their riſing.</item>
                     <item>3. Quality of the raiſed.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Second onely of theſe is, what we are engaged to take cognizance of, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks to, <hi>v.</hi> 23. — <hi>though we ſhall all be made alive,</hi> yet will it be done in a certain method, every man in his own order. Chriſt himſelf roſe firſt, as the firſt fruits of them that ſleep; but the whole crop of Chriſtians ſhall not riſe till his ſecond coming, which the Apoſtle having mentioned, he ſpends the five follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verſes (by way of digreſſion) in ſetting down of this coming of Chriſt.
<list>
                     <item>1. What ſhall follow it.</item>
                     <item>2. To what end.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. What follows it, you have from <hi>Verſe</hi> 23. to the Text incluſively, in theſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169964:9"/>five Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The end of the world.</item>
                     <item>2. The delivery up of Chriſts Kingdom.</item>
                     <item>3. The putting down of all Rule, and all Authority and Power.</item>
                     <item>4. The ſubduing of all Enemies.</item>
                     <item>5. The ſubjection of the Son himſelf.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. To what end, and this you have in the Text, <hi>That God may be all in all.</hi> That theſe few words may the better be underſtood, I ſhall ſay a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to each of theſe three things, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Their reference.</item>
                     <item>2. Their aim.</item>
                     <item>3. Their meaning.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, To what paſſages of the Chapter do they carry a relation? to me, truly, they ſeem to be the reſult of all, and of each of thoſe five things but now mentioned: The world ſhall be ended. Chriſts Kingdom ſhall be delivered up. All Rule, and all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Power, ſhall be put down. All Enemies ſhall be ſubdued. The
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169964:10"/>Son himſelf ſhall be ſubject, and all, and every one of theſe, <hi>That God may be all in all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, their aym is to hold us out, wherein conſiſteth the Final, and perfect Happineſs of the People of God, they be high expreſſions, and doe ſignifie ſome incomprehenſible glory, flowing from God himſelf, which the Saints ſhall be filled with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis iſtis verbis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſibilis, quaedam gloria, quae a Deo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manans nos totos, implebit.</hi> Beza in locum.</note>. We ſhall be the readier to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it, if we conſider theſe</p>
               <div type="particulars">
                  <head>Four Particulars.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. 'Tis plainly much of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles deſign in this Chapter, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince Beleevers of a condition here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, perfectly glorious and happy; if their portion in the next world, ſhould be no better then it is in this, they were of all men moſt miſerable, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19. which would be abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abſurd to imagine of a people for whom Chriſt dyed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That this happineſs is not ſo compleat and full, as it ſhall be.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169964:10"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Till all enemies be ſubdued, and the laſt of all deſtroyed, which is death. Nor,</item>
                        <item>2. So long as Chriſt reigns by virtue of his Mediatorſhip, and therefore this Kingdome muſt firſt be delivered up to God the Father.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The end of Chriſts taking up this mediatory Kingdome (next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hither Gods glory) was the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Beleevers to the higheſt pitch of felicity that they are capable of, and ſo it cannot be otherwiſe, but that,</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The accompliſhment of this end muſt needs fall in with the laſt reſult of the adminiſtration of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and that in the language of the Text, is, <hi>That God may be All, in All.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, for the meaning of theſe words, they are a Periphraſis of our compleat enjoyment of God. <hi>That God may be All, in All;</hi> is, That we may enjoy him al one to all purpoſes,
<note n="*" place="margin">Sebaſt. Mejerus in locum.</note>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Zanch. de</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">Ds</hi> 
                        <hi>Eloh. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c</hi> 11.</note> neither wanting, nor willing any thing beſides him,
<note n="*" place="margin">Aqu in locum.</note> when nothing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169964:11"/>ſhall be in us that is not as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<note n="*" place="margin">Aqu. in locum.</note> in whom the ſoul ſhall totally acquieſce, and who alone ſhall be its bleſſedneſs.</p>
                  <p>For a perſon to be all in all to me, is for me to have ſuch an enjoyment of him to all purpoſes, as that I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do, nor have need to enjoy any thing elſe: for God to be ſo to his Saints, is for them to enjoy, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with, to have to do with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but God.</p>
                  <p>Look back again upon the relation between theſe words, and the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent verſes, and you may diſcern in them ſuch an enjoyment of God as ſhall be,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Without partners. <hi>God ſhall be all,</hi> we ſhall have nothing elſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Without defect. <hi>God ſhall be all, in all:</hi> every thing to every purpoſe.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Deus ipſe nobis omnia ſuppedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabit, quippe qui &amp; cibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, &amp; potus, &amp; amictus &amp;c. fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus est. Athan. in locum. Deus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit vita &amp; ſalus, &amp; vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, &amp; gloria, &amp; omnia. Aqu. in locum. Aug. de Civit. Dei. l.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 30.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Without means. Word and Sacraments and the like, in which God is enjoyed here, ſhall ceaſe, that Kingdome where theſe adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are made uſe of, <hi>ſhal be delivered up,</hi> ver. 24.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:169964:11"/> 4. Without oppoſition. <hi>All ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall be ſubdued,</hi> Ver. 25.</p>
                  <p>Without end. <hi>Death ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,</hi> Verſ. 26. and even our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhall be raiſed in incorruption, and ſhall put on immortality.</p>
                  <p>All this I conceive to be in the Text, though I cannot ſay that this is all.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>The Doctrines of the Text propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and one of them opened.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe words of the Text do now plainly lay us down theſe two Propoſitions, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The higheſt happineſs of the Saints, is the enjoyment of God.</item>
                  <item>2. That enjoyment of God which is the Saints higheſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhall be immediate, Sole, free, full and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
               </list>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:169964:12"/>
                  <head>Firſt Propoſition.</head>
                  <p>The higheſt happineſs of the Saints is the enjoyment of God.</p>
                  <p>For the Explication of which, it wil be neceſſary to enquire what
<list>
                        <item>1. The enjoyment of God is.</item>
                        <item>2. Is our higheſt happineſs.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Firſt, What is the enjoyment of God?</head>
                  <p>You may not expect an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this while we are on this ſide Heaven, we are not fully agreed what enjoyment is, of which ſeveral men have ſeveral apprehenſions; and as much as we can well doe, is to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what God is not.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quid non ſit, quam quid ſit. Aug. in Pſ.</hi> 86.8.</note> All I ſhall adventure upon is but this offer, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the enjoyment of God there muſt not be a concurrence of (at leaſt) theſe four things, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:169964:12"/>
                     <item>1. Knowledge of him.</item>
                     <item>2. Influences from him.</item>
                     <item>3. Acquieſcence in him.</item>
                     <item>4. Converſe with him.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Firſt, The knowledge of God. We can never enjoy what we have no acquaintance with,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitis. Aug. l.</hi> 10. <hi>de Trinit.</hi>
                     </note> our deſires can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo much as move after an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known object, how much leſs can they be ſatisfied with it. Knowledge is the intellectual eye which the ſoul ſees by and when our ſight ſhall be at the cleareſt, our enjoyment ſhall be at the higheſt, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</p>
                  <p>But it muſt be the knowledge of God in Chriſt, to know him other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, is to ſee too much in him of terrour, for us to approach unto; a wad of ſtubble is not very well quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for any communion with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire. We cannot walk toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther except we be agreed, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.3. and God is no where but in Chriſt, reconciling ſinners unto himſelf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19.</p>
                  <p>Neither is it every Knowledge of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169964:13"/>God in Chriſt, that will let us in to the enjoyment of him, it muſt be influential upon our hearts and practiſes; if our actions drive a trade of contradiction to our intellectuals, and our lives keep no correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy without profeſſion, God will not know us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23. And how much weaker then a Spiders web, is that poor mans hope, who in ſuch a caſe ſhall but dream to enjoy him? an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding head is not qualification enough for this happineſs, thoſe whom God owns, are men of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hearts.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtles great aym, is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of Chriſt, and its inlet into the ſoul, is by the way of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: upon this account it is that he throws dung in the face of all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments elſe, that he may know Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10.</p>
                  <p>And thus whom God means to to hold communion with, he doth firſt let into his acquaintance, by opening.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:169964:13"/>
                     <item>1. His own face.</item>
                     <item>2. Their underſtandings.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Firſt, His own face, for he is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a God that hideth himſelf, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.15. and in ſuch a caſe is not diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enough to be enjoied, hence ſurely is it, that when the Saints would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their comfortable apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their God, they beſeech him not to hide his face from them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.7. And when he is at any time out of ſight, that darkneſs is left upon their ſpirits, ther's no way to ſet him within their view again, but the lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of his countenance, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering of his face to ſhine upon them: and for this it is that the Saints are ſo often upon their knees. <hi>Lord lift thou up the light of thy countenance upon us. Pſal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Make thy face to ſhine upon thy ſervant, Pſalm</hi> 31.16. but this is not enough, unleſs God open,</p>
                  <p>Second, Our underſtandings. The Well and <hi>Hagar</hi> in the Wilderneſs, were neer enough one to the other,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169964:14"/>yet till God opened her eyes ſhe did not ſee it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.19. Chriſt was with his Diſciples, yet whileſt their eyes were held they did not know him, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.16. look in what degree the Lord is pleaſed to open our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, in ſuch a degree we appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend him; even thoſe diſcoveries of God that are in Scripture, are by none of us any further receiveable, then himſelf makes them way. Chriſt opened their underſtandings, that they might underſtand the Scriptures, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.45. He had opened the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture before, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 27. And ſo there was light enough about the object; but this did not ſuffice, till there was light too in the faculty, till he had opened their underſtandings to let it in. Our underſtanding is <hi>Dei Infun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibulum</hi> (ſo I have heard it called) Gods Tunnel, which he doth inlarge according to the infuſions which he is pleaſed to afford us of himſelf. This is the firſt requiſite to enjoyment, the Knowledge of God. How ſad is the condition of ignorant ſouls? then
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169964:14"/>may they come to the enjoyment of God, when mid-night may dwell in the ſun. <hi>What communion hath light with darkneſs,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Influences from God. When we receive all that God can afford, and we are capable of, as aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances of his being ours, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences of his being ours, to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purpoſes, with that peace paſſing all underſtanding, and that joy unſpeakable and full of glory, which is wont to wait upon ſuch a condition, ſo <hi>Solomon</hi> calls that the enjoyment of a thing, when it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives unto us all the good that it can afford; <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.18.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Acquieſcence in God, as neither finding contentation in any thing leſs, nor deſiring a jot more; To enjoy God is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Frui, eſt amore inhaerere alicui rei propter ſeipſam. Aq.</hi> 1ae. 2ae <hi>Qu.</hi> 11. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</note> to love God, and to cleave unto him for his own ſake.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Frui est uti cum gaudio &amp; dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatione, Lomb. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> 'Tis to poſſeſs God with compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, and all poſſible ſatisfaction:
<note n="*" place="margin">Suavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam de ultimo fine, Aqu. quo ſup.</note> 'Tis a ſweetneſs taſted in God, even to the raviſhing of our affections, as much of this as is enjoyable here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169964:15"/>you have a reliſh of in theſe and the like Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.34. to which add, That Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven which is not above the reach of Saints upon earth, in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. which Scriptures I hope you will have time enough to turn to, and dwell upon, till all that delight, and Sweetneſs, Acquieſcence, Compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie and ſatisfaction in God, dropt thither from the boſome of thoſe Saints, be taken out, and copyed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your own ſpirits.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Converſe with God. Then we enjoy him, when he dwels and walkes in us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. by his ſpirit, graces, comforts, when we walk with him upon earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24. and converſe with him in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Secondly, What is our higheſt Happineſs?</head>
                  <p>I think their deſcription of Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to be full enough, who make it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169964:15"/>to conſiſt in the poſſeſſion of a perfect good, excluding every evil, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying every deſire
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Aqu.</hi> 1ae. 2ae. <hi>Q.</hi> 5. <hi>Art.</hi> 3.</note>.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Poſſeſſion. It may be ſome degree of Happineſs to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled to ſuch a good in reverſion; but the height of happineſs it cannot be, where any thing deſireable is wanting, it is an abatement of feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of a perfect good. All things and every thing, that may be called by that name, <hi>bleſſedneſs,</hi> is a condition made up of the aggregation of all good things, not one muſt be left out; yet is it not neceſſary that we poſſeſs every good in kind, 'tis enough that the good we poſſeſs, be as much as every good in value.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Excluding every evil, both of ſin and ſuffering, when either of theſe are incident to a condition: either that condition is not happy, or theſe are not evil, as long as we can either ſin or ſuffer, we are under ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of infelicity.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Satisfying every deſire, when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169964:16"/>we are ſo filled with the good we have, that as we do not want, ſo we cannot wiſh a jot more. So you have the point explained.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>The Point propounded, proved by ſome Scriptures.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AL thoſe Scriptures may pertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be called in to the making good of this propoſition, which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert our higheſt happineſs to conſiſt in Gods preſence, in being with God, in ſeeing God, in being ſatisfied with God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are all but diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied expreſſions of our enjoyment of God. I ſhal take theſe that follow into conſideration, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. <hi>In thy preſence is fulneſs of joy, at thy right hand there are pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Here is fulneſs of joy, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of pleaſures: and is not this a plain deſcription of our higheſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? ſo Chriſt the Head, had this joy ſet before him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169964:16"/>when he puts any member of his into poſſeſſion of that Kingdom which was prepared for him from the foundation of the world, his livery of Seiſin is conceived in theſe terms: <hi>Enter thou into the joy of thy Lord, Mat.</hi> 25.21. I have not met with one Expoſition, that doth not find in this aſſertion of <hi>David</hi> (or rather of Chriſt in <hi>Davids</hi> perſon) a plain diſcription of our high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt happineſs. But where is all this to be found? Why</p>
               <p n="2">2. In Gods preſence, or in Gods face, and is not this as plain a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the enjoyment of God? the ſhewing of whoſe face, doth ſignifie ſuch a manifeſtation of himſelf, as doth let us ſo into his acquaintance, as we are wont to be in theirs, with whom we familiarly converſe. Sometimes the face of God ſeems to be full of frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.6. tis his ſmiling face that is here mentioned. God hath ſmiles of grace for us, whileſt we are in our journey,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 4.6.</note> theſe are ſmiles of glory, when we ſhall come home, the twilight of his Countenance is our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169964:17"/>of him here, the full noon of it ſhall be ſo hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.15. <hi>I ſhall be ſatisfied, when I awake with thy likeneſs.</hi> Here is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deſire full, and what doth fill them but Gods Image? ſome expound this of Chriſt, the expreſs Image of his fathers perſon, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. and what doth this amount to leſs then the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God? There be three ſorts of Images. 1. <hi>Imago repreſentationis</hi> ſo there is ſomething of God in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inferior creatures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. 2. <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ſimilitudinis;</hi> ſo there is much of God in man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. 3. <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go aequalitatis,</hi> and ſo there is all of God in Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9. Others make glory and Image all one, as they are made. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.7. and this the ſenſe, when I ſhall awake up out of the duſt, and have admiſſion to ſee and enjoy thy glorious preſence,
<note n="*" place="margin">Poſt hanc vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do clarè Deum. Lorin in locum.</note> I ſhall be ſatisfied with that object; neither ſhall I want, or deſire any more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.8. Bleſſedneſs is placed in ſeeing of God, and who is it that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169964:17"/>writes upon this ſubject, but doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it to conſiſt in any thing elſe
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecta bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo non poteſt eſſe niſi in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinae eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiae. Aq.</hi> 1ae. 2ae. <hi>Q.</hi> 3. <hi>Art.</hi> 8. <hi>vid. apud. Dionyſ. Carhuſ. in</hi> 4. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 49. <hi>q.</hi> 4.</note>? when Chriſt prays for the glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of beleevers, his requeſt is, <hi>They may be with him. Joh.</hi> 17.24. what are the earneſt groanings of the Saints for, but to be preſent with the Lord? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. the great comfort that <hi>Paul</hi> preſcribes againſt all that death can do, is, <hi>That we ſhall be with the Lord.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. and what is the ods between our grace and glory, but this, <hi>That now we ſee through a glaſs darkly, but then we ſhall ſee face to face, now we know in part, but then we ſhall know even as we are known,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. to enjoy God face to face, and to know God in the ſame manner (for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as, is a note of ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, not of equality) though not in the ſame degree that God knows us, is the top of our beatitude, which in 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. is ſaid to conſiſt in ſeeing God as he is, ſuch a viſion onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compleatly beatifical.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:169964:18"/>
               <head>SECT IIII. <hi>Reaſons of the Point.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat our higheſt Happineſs is the enjoyment of God, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (you ſee) bear ſufficient witneſſe, the reaſons why 'tis ſo may be wrapt up in this one.</p>
               <p>There is in God, what ever is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to a perfect happineſſe, and it is not in any thing elſe.</p>
               <p>That what our felicity is made up of muſt be good, is beyond diſpute: evil, as ſuch, cannot be the object of any appetite, much leſſe can it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded as the laſt end by any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent that is rational,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſtac. Eth. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te</hi> 1a. <hi>in initi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Aq.</hi> 1ae. 2ae. <hi>qu. Art.</hi> 1.</note> yet will not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very good reach far enough to make us happy, it muſt be</p>
               <p n="1">1. A pure and ſimple good. If there bee in it any mixture of evil, 'twil never do it, if it be penal, it is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſenſe, and then there is ſomthing more, or elſe of loſs, and then there is ſomething leſs then can conſtitute a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169964:18"/>bleſſedneſſe: if it be ſinful, the caſe is worſe, becauſe the evil is greater
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Culpa habet plus de ratione mali quam pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> Aqu. <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>Qu</hi> 48. <hi>Art.</hi> 6.</note>, if it be pardoned, yet 'tis a burthen to be groan'd under, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. if it be not, it leaves us open to the Curſe, <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.10.</p>
               <p>Now ſuch a good is God, Light in whom <hi>there is no darkneſſe at all,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.5. Light here below is <hi>puriſsima qualitas,</hi> very pure and ſimple, yet ſcarce enough ſo to be a ſhadow of that above, which no man can approach unto, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16. God is a good in which there is no evil at all.</p>
               <p>But nothing elſe is ſo; the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Creature is mixt with ſomething that is not good, how could they elſe be vanity and vexation of ſpirit? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſufficient good: Let us (at leaſt in a ſuppoſition) be free from evil; yet if the good we have be not enough, we are under a condition of want and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digencie, and can that be happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</p>
               <p>Such is God, a good that is all-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, as he cals himſelf, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. able
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169964:19"/>to afford what ever, is deſireable
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In quo nihil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderari poſſit bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</hi> Zanch. <hi>de nat. dei</hi> l. 4. c. 1. Qu. 1.</note> an immenſe fulneſſe, an ocean of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, containing in himſelf all the good that is in other things with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible overplus: There is no good in Wife, Child, Friend, Health, Beauty, Honour, Learning, Wiſdom, Wealth, Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but is all found in one God; though not <hi>formalitèr,</hi> the ſame in kind, yet <hi>eminentèr,</hi> more infinitely, more than the ſame in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bold <hi>Ser. in</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. <hi>p.</hi> 6.</note> the whole world and God put together are not a jot more excellent than God alone: For if there be any excellency in the Creature, 'tis more eminently in God already, and your addition will ſignifie nothing:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. in Pſ.</hi> 27.9.</note> 
                  <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God will beſtow upon me, let him take it all away, and give me himſelf,</hi> it was <hi>Auguſtines</hi> offer, and he knew his bargain would have been good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
               <p>But nothing elſe is ſo: All the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the world, if they ſtand by themſelves are but ſo many cyphers, unleſſe God (as a ſolid number) be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them they ſignifie nothing: Set
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169964:19"/>God aſide, and there is not an all-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency in the whole Creation for one ſoul. He that hath moſt of the world hath not enough, and he that hath leaſt hath too much, if he cannot ſay with him,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Omnis copia quae non eſt Deus meus, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi egeſtas eſt.</hi> Aug. <hi>Solil. q.c.</hi> 13.</note> All abundance, if it be not my God, is to me nothing but poverty and want. It muſt be</p>
               <p n="3">3. A ſatisfying good; able to fill, quiet, and content the Soul. Delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is of the eſſence of happineſſe, and is cauſed by the ſatisfaction
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ete appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titûs in bono a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>depto.</hi> Aqu. 1. 2. <hi>Qu.</hi> 4. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</note> of our deſires in the good which we poſſeſſe. Whatever we have, if it be not enough to ſilence our appetite from craving more, we are ſhort of happineſſe.</p>
               <p>Such is God; beyond whom there being nothing imaginable, its impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble there ſhould be any thing deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Plato</hi> himſelf could define God to be
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num quo nihil me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogitarri poteſt Ex</hi> Zanch. <hi>de nat. Dei. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Qu.</hi> 1.</note> the chiefeſt good, than which nothing better can fall ſo much as within our imagination. Surely the good that God is, as well as the good he can do, is above all that we are able to think, exceeding abundantly above it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.20.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:169964:20"/>
               <p> But nothing elſe is ſo: Leave God out, &amp; whatever you take in, the heart will ſtil be capable of deſiring more; all the world cannot fil it, nor can all the creatures that it is ſtockt withall give a compleat ſatisfaction to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of one ſoul. Is it becauſe what is ſpherical (as the world is) can never fil what is triangular (as the heart is) but ſome places will be ſtil empty? or is it that our concupiſcible faculty is of ſo large a ſize that the whole earth and the fulneſſe thereof cannot fit it? or that no creature can fil two places at once, as money for example, the cheſt, and the heart at the ſame time? or is it the unſutableneſſe that is between that object and this faculty? or is our appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite raiſed by having, as a fire is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the fuel it is fed withall? or is it rather becauſe we naturally are carried out after our own perfection, and ſo cannot terminate our deſires in any thing that is ſhort of it, as all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are? what ever is the reaſon of it, ſure we are, that he that loveth ſilver ſhall not be ſatisfied with ſilver; nor
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169964:20"/>he that loveth abundance with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, <hi>Eecleſ.</hi> 5.10. As nothing can be the perfection, ſo nothing can be the ſatisfaction of the ſoul, but he that made it: She will never be at reſt till ſhe reſt in God: there's no ful content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in her pilgrimage, and her onely home is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Animae patria eſt Deus ipſe.</hi> Aug.</note> God himſelfe; no good but the chiefeſt can ſuffice us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:169964:21"/>
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>The further illuſtration of the point.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere will a little more of light be let in upon the Doctrine, we have under conſideration, from theſe three particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt: The happineſſe we have here is that enjoyment of God which we have here, and look at what rate our enjoyment is, at the ſame is our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and for this we will be tried, by
<list>
                     <item>1. God, and</item>
                     <item>2. His Saints.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, doth not God promiſe this as the greateſt happineſſe? <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.45. <hi>I will dwel amongſt the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and will be their God (i. e.)</hi> I will ſettle mine habitation and divine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence among you,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ainſw. <hi>in locum.</hi>
                  </note> it was the greateſt ſign of Gods grace towards his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. in Ex.</hi> 25.8</note> and the promiſe of it is noted to wrap up in it an eminent bleſſing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. compared with <hi>chap.</hi> 6.16.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169964:21"/>And on the other ſide, it is a wo with an emphaſis unto a people when the Lord ſhall depart from them, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9.12.</p>
               <p>Secondly: Whether the Saints do not look upon that enjoyment of God which is afforded them on earth, as their greateſt happineſſe, till they ſhal have more of it in heaven, is eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by obſerving in them theſe five things, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Before all things in the world they deſire this, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 27.4. <hi>One thing have I deſired of the Lord, that will I ſeek after; that I may dwel in the houſe of the Lord, all the daies of my life to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the beauty of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. To ſee, or behold it, is to enjoy it, is this one thing all that <hi>David</hi> would have? Do we not ever and anon find him upon his knees before the throne of Grace, for one bleſſing or other beſide this? We doe ſo; but this one thing eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, this bleſſing above any other: This is it that the Saints pant after, as <hi>the Hart panteth after the water brooks,</hi> Pſal. 42.1, 2.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:169964:22"/> 2. Above all things in the world they prize this; 'tis not the encreaſe of Corn and Wine, but the light of Gods countenance which they value, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6.7. his loving kindneſſe is better than the life it ſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.3. than any life, what ingredients ſoever may be in it to make it valuable: And yet what a rate are we wont to ſet our lives at! men will bleed, ſweat, vomit, purge, be cupp'd, ſcarified, wear iſſues, plaiſters, part with an eſtate, yea with a limb or two to preſerve their lives; as he cries out, give me any deformity, any tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, any miſery, ſo you ſpare my life
<note n="*" place="margin">Debilem facito manu, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lem pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, coxâ, tuber ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berum &amp;c. vita dum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne eſt.</note>. It is reported that Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi> could not endure ſo much as to hear death named
<note n="*" place="margin">Sen. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 101.</note>; and <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh of <hi>France</hi> was ſaid to be of the ſame temper: ſo doe men prize their lives, but yet a value infinitely above it doe the Saints ſet upon the enjoyment of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No loſs in the world lies ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy upon their ſpirits as the loſſe of this. Other afflictions may make him cry, but under this they cannot chuſe but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169964:22"/>roare, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.8. others may make their bones ake, this doth break them in pieces, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.8. is there any pain more tormenting then of broken bones? yet this doth <hi>David</hi> pitch upon to offer you a gueſe at that ſmart which ſeized upon his ſpirit, under a loſs of communion with his God. <hi>Job</hi> can loſe his eſtate, his ſervants, his children, and be quiet, <hi>Job</hi> 1. But when the Arrows of the Almighty are within him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> his grief is then heavyer then the ſand of the Sea, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.2.3.4. Outward loſſes to ſome men have been unſufferably afflictive,
<note n="*" place="margin">Roger. Epiſc. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſb. tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phani-Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utus opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentiam verſus eſt Nubri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſ.</note> one being turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of his eſtate runs out of his wits ed out of his eſtate runs out of his wits
<note n="*" place="margin">Aegeus in mare ſe praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dedit Plut. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ejus.</note> another for the death of a ſon, throws himſelf headlong into the Sea. This to the Saints is comparatively nothing, their great loſſe is to loſe the ſight of their God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Nothing can trouble them, whileſt they have this, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4. <hi>Though I walk through the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will fear no evil:</hi> There is danger enough, the hazard of life is as little as can be ſignified by the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169964:23"/>of death, can death it ſelf be far, when we are within, yea when we walk through the ſhaddow of it? or take the valley of the ſhaddow of death to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie ſo thick a darkneſs as the grave is covered withal, whether death car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries us; yet it is a ſuppoſition of a condition black and dreadful enough, how hard a matter is it, not to have ſome degree of affrightment upon us in the dark? not to be afraid of the terrour by night hath, and therefore needs a divine promiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.5. <hi>Augustus</hi> that great Emperour, durſt not ſit in the dark
<note n="*" place="margin">niſi ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et. vita ejus.</note> without company, and was it not in thoughts from the viſions of the night, that fear come upon <hi>Iob,</hi> and trembling which made all his bones to ſhake, <hi>Iob.</hi> 4.13.14. amongſt thoſe very many acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of darkneſs which are in Scripture, doth one of them ſignifie any thing that is not uncomfortable? Here is you ſee matter enough of danger, yet no fear of it, and whence all this holy ſecurity, but from the preſence of God? <hi>I will fear no evil for thou art
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169964:23"/>with me:</hi> See alſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.1.2.3. much to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Nothing can comfort them if they want this.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoc ſcio do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ine deus meus, quia ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſum ſine te ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le eſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi Aug. Soliloq. cap.</hi> 13.</note> What wanted <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> of any outward bleſſing, when thoſe expreſſions fell from him, in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 30.6.7. <hi>In my proſperity I ſaid I ſhall never be moved. Lord by thy favor thou haſt made my Mountain to ſtand ſtrong;</hi> but ſee what follows: <hi>Thou didſt hide thy face, and I was troubled, thou with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewedſt the ſence of thy favour and lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Molle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus in loc.</note> 
                  <hi>which I had fondly enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and miſerable comforters did I then find all other enjoyments,</hi> and indeed: <hi>When God giveth quietneſs, who then can make trouble? and when he hideth his face, who then can behold him? whether it be done againſt a Nation, or againſt a man onely, Job</hi> 34.29.</p>
               <p>This is one thing that doth illuſtrate the point we have in hand: That at what rate our enjoyment of God is here below, at the ſame is our happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and for this the Lord himſelf and his Saints, have given in their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict,</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:169964:24"/> 2. Gods own bleſſedneſſſe doth conſiſt in the enjoyment of himſelf: For if we beleeve the Schoolmen,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lomb</hi> 1. <hi>Dist.</hi> 1. <hi>g.</hi>
                  </note> he doth not enjoy any thing elſe: he hath ſome uſe of the Creatures, but no Fruition, or if he had, there is not in them that abſolute freedom from evil, nor perfection of goodneſſe which is requiſite unto happineſſe that muſt needs be Gods bleſſedneſſe which he aimeth at, and reſteth in as his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt and laſt end; but that God in all his actions and adminiſtrations aimeth at, and reſteth ſo in himſelf, beſides the teſtimony of diverſe Scriptures,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.4. <hi>Apo.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.32. <hi>Apo.</hi> 4.11 <hi>Iſ.</hi> 43.7.21.</note> ſeems even by reaſon it ſelf not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be demonſtrated: Let us look upon theſe</p>
               <div type="propositions">
                  <head>Six Propoſitions.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Prop.</hi> All things in their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and actings, aym at ſome end or other which they may Acquieſce and reſt in
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ariſt,</hi> 2. <hi>Phyſ. c.</hi> 8. <hi>Text.</hi> 77. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note>. If this Propoſition were doubted, it would be proved by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that God and Nature do nothing in vain.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Prop.</hi> The end of all deſigns
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169964:24"/>and actings (at leaſt in every reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nature) is ſomething that is good, either truly ſo, or in appearance, (ſee before Sect. 4. about the beginning) hence is good in general defined to be that which all do deſire
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Id quod omnia ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petunt.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt. 1. <hi>Eth.</hi>
                     </note>.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Prop.</hi> The laſt end of all motions and actings in every reaſonable nature, is the chiefeſt good: All, even natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally deſiring to be bleſſed and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<note n="*" place="margin">Scot. <hi>in</hi> 4. <hi>Sent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iſt.</hi> 49. <hi>Q.</hi> 9.</note>, though many doe not diſtinctly know what happineſs is, or which is the way to it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Prop.</hi> If there were no blindneſſe in our underſtandings, that we could with clearneſſe apprehend what the chiefeſt good were, nor any perverſity in our wils to rebel againſt the dictates of our underſtandings, wee ſhould then particularly and diſtinctly aim at it, and reſt in it.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Prop.</hi> This chiefeſt good is God; being good naturally, independently, perfectly; and the onely cauſe of all that good, which is any where elſe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Prop.</hi> God perfectly and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly knows himſelf to be the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169964:25"/>good
<note n="*" place="margin">Aq. <hi>part</hi> 1. <hi>Q.</hi> 14. <hi>Art.</hi> 2.3.</note>, his underſtanding is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.5. From all which it ſeems to look like an impoſſibility that God ſhould aim at, or reſt in any thing as his laſt end but himſelf. This is the Second. The bleſſedneſs of God himſelfe is the enjoyment of himſelfe before any thing elſe was, he was the bleſſed God, neither hath he received any addition to his happineſſe by the things which he hath made.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly: The greateſt miſery of the damned in hell is, that they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the enjoyment of God
<note n="*" place="margin">Biel <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit. Can. miſſ. lect.</hi> 33. e.</note>; this is enough to make a hell of it ſelfe, yea it hath ten thouſand hels in the womb of it. What is that darkneſſe which the damned are threatned to be caſt into? not the abſence of the light of the Sun; for the Saints in heaven have not this light, becauſe they need it not, and how ſhould ſuch a darkneſſe be any puniſhment to the condemned Angels, who never made any uſe of ſuch a light? It is rather the abſence of the light of heaven, which is God himſelf
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>See</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſ. cont.</hi> 20. <hi>Q.</hi> 5.</note>. Surely that the damned are
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169964:25"/>ſaid to weep and to gnaſh their teeth, doth proceed from the greateſt of their torments, which Chriſt tels us ſhall be from this, when they ſhall ſee <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> and all the Prophets in the Kingdom of God, and they themſelves thruſt out, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.28.</p>
                  <p>Puniſhment of ſenſe, though it be infinite as to the duration of it, yet as to its extremity we may have leave to judge otherwiſe: for if it were infinite (not to mention how inconſiſtent this would be with that diverſity of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in the pains of hell, which (with good countenance from Scripture
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.14, 15. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.47, 48.</note>) is by many beleeved;) it would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that God could not puniſh them a jot more, but it is a <hi>medium</hi> by which we are wont to prove the Lords omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, that he never doth ſo much in reference to the creature, but that he is ſtill able to doe more
<note n="*" place="margin">Zanch. <hi>de nat. Dei, l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 3.</note>: So what the damned ſuffer in their pain of ſenſe is but a finite evill, what they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from in their pain of loſſe, is an infinite good. 'Tis in Gods power
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169964:26"/>to lay upon them a greater evil than what they ſuffer, 'tis not in his power to deny them a greater good than what they want.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>Firſt Uſe, for information.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEt us from this Doctrine in the firſt place, ſee what may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded for the better information of our judgements. It follows,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That God is of a tranſcendent and infinite goodneſſe; both</p>
               <p n="1">1. In himſelfe: Many good things doe we read of in the Scripture, and of many perſons that are paſſed under that character
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 11.24.</note>, and yet we are told again, that <hi>there is none good but one, that is God,</hi> Mat. 19.17. Are there contradictions in the Scripture? or is not this the meaning, that goodneſſe is not any where at the rate that it is in God? 'Tis in God originally, 'tis in the creature but by way of participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169964:26"/>in him as in a fountain, in them but as in a veſſel; in him univerſally, in them but to ſome purpoſes; in him an ocean, in them but a drop; theirs ſo deficient that they need ſomething elſe to their happineſſe in earth; Gods ſo full, that we ſhall need nothing elſe to our happineſſe in heaven. How tranſcendently good is our God, that even in heaven it ſelf nothing but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf can make us bleſſed! we have none in heaven but him, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 73.25. and,</p>
               <p n="2">2. To all his people, that he will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow himſelf upon them: What he promiſed to the Father of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full he will make good to all his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, he will be our exceeding great reward, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. not cauſally in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving other things, but formally in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving himſelf, the reward and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder ſhall be all one: Said the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel to <hi>Abraham, Now I know that thou feareſt God, ſeeing thou haſt not withheld thy ſon, thine onely ſon from me,</hi> Gen. 22.12. May we not a little vary the expreſſions, and ſend them back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain?
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169964:27"/>Lord, now we know that thou loveſt man, ſeeing thou doeſt not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy ſelf, thine own ſelf from him. Let out your underſtandings to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt, and conceive if you can, what, and how great a good that is which is God himſelf
<note n="*" place="margin">Aug. <hi>in manuali cap.</hi> 33. <hi>Quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; quale eſt illud bonum quod deus eſt.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Secondly: That of thoſe things which are afforded us here below, in ſuch of them there is moſt of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in which there is moſt of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God. In his Ordinances eſpecially is God wont to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and to offer himſelf to be enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there's his preſence in the midſt of us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.20. there he walks, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.1. there his beauty is to be beheld, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. the God and King of his Saints may be ſeen going in his San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 68.24. here is moſt of God; and ſee if the Scriptures doe not place here, upon this account, moſt of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.4.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterii ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terni commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datio dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genter hic eſt obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, &amp;c.</hi> Mollerus <hi>in locum.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed is the man whom thou chooſeſt, and cauſeſt to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto thee, that he may dwel in thy Courts, he ſhall be ſatisfied with the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy houſe; even of thy holy
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169964:27"/>temple.</hi> Read the 84 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and if <hi>David</hi> may be judge there is more of heaven in the Ordinances, than can be enjoyed any where elſe, till we come thither.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That thoſe men give us a falſe draught of heaven, who doe not place it in the enjoyment of God. The Heathens had their <hi>Elizium</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">— <hi>per amplum mittimur Elyzium.</hi> Virg. <hi>Aen.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 744.</note>, where they ſuppoſed good mens ſouls to take up their habitation
<note n="*" place="margin">Vbi pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</note>, which ſome place in the earth, ſome in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, others in the ſphere of the Moon, full of all delights that are imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vives in</hi> Aug. <hi>in civit. dei. l.</hi> 21. <hi>c. ult</hi>
                  </note> but theſe poor ſoules knew not God. The <hi>Turks</hi> have their Paradiſe where they expect a felicitie in the enjoyment of ſilken Carpets, pleaſant Rivers, fruitful Trees, beautiful Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Muſick, good cheere, and choice Wines, precious Stones, Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Plate, and ſuch conceits as theſe
<note n="*" place="margin">Roſſe View of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, §. 6. <hi>p.</hi> 146.</note>. And what have
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Martiniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>de verâ Religione in</hi> 8vo. <hi>p.</hi> 119.120.</note> ſome dream'd of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven amongſt Chriſtians? Sure ſome of a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a return of the ſoul into another body; ſome of an eternal life, ſomwhere out of the kingdome of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169964:28"/>God; others of a happineſſe made up of ſenſuality and the pleaſures of the fleſh, and many ignorant perſons call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſtians amongſt us, have but a very little more refined apprehenſions of the joyes of heaven; ſuppoſing them no others than may very near be enjoied by the beaſts of the field. This is a happyneſſe fancied by thoſe who cannot taſt what God is, which muſt firſt be done, before we can ſo much as gueſſe what heaven is.</p>
               <p>Fourthly: That amongſt thoſe many pretenders to a deſire of going to heaven, the greateſt number do it either not knowingly, or not heartily; for as much as they deſire not the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God. Is this a ſlander? oh how contentedly, how joyfully ſhould I doe penance for reporting it, did it not appear to be a ſad truth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In ſome by their proclamation of defiance to the ordinary means and waies of enjoying God; and are not the Ordinances of the Goſpel ſuch? and how ſufficiently theſe have been mocked, and buffeted, and ſpit upon,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169964:28"/>is too well known. Yea have there not been clamours that they might be crucified? How many will not at all own them, how many doe ſeldome or never uſe them? there be a woful num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that will have nothing to doe with preaching, or praying, that will not ſo much as call upon God once or twice a day in their families, you cannot men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion an ordinance, but they are above it; doe theſe men deſire to enjoy any communion with God, who will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hear him, nor ſpeak to him? yea not ſo much as bid him good night, or good morrow?</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>There be many good people, who doubtleſs deſire to enjoy God, who own not the Ordinances,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> To that fancy of enjoying God here without Ordinances, I may ſpeak ſomething when I ſhall come to the ſecond Doctrine, <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. In the mean time, as to the goodneſs of the perſons, I ſhall lay before you theſe four parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Perhaps all the teſtimony they have of their goodneſſe is from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169964:29"/>or from others very near of the ſame character, or at beſt from the miſtaken charity of ſuch as are godly indeed. However</p>
               <p n="2">2. This is no expreſſion of their goodneſſe, being a ſin againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and directions of the Goſpel. See 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17.20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24.</p>
               <p n="3">3. 'Tis not a goodneſs that good men formerly were wont to be guilty of. <hi>David</hi> was not. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. and 84.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and 122.1. If theſe three, <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> were here, they would not do ſo. See 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Iob</hi> 23.12.</p>
               <p n="4">4. 'T was not accounted goodneſſe in the dayes of old, not in the time of <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 28.9. nor of <hi>Iſaiah, Iſ.</hi> 30.9, 10. nor of <hi>Ieremiah, Ier.</hi> 11.10. nor of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.28. nor of the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46. Wee muſt finde out a new definition of goodneſſe, or ſome other way to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe ours than by laying aſide the Ordinances of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In others, by their trading in thoſe practices which they cannot expect
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169964:29"/>the enjoyment of God in. There be divers (even among pretenders to Religion) who walk licentiouſly and looſely, ſpending a great part of their precious time, in rioting and drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſſe, chambering and wantonneſſe, for whom the Apoſtles character of thoſe whom he could not mention without teares is as fit as if it had been made for them, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18. Doe theſe men deſire the enjoyment of <hi>God,</hi> who daily put themſelves into an incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it? are not theſe practices works of darkneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12? and is not God light, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.5? and what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion between theſe two, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14? Pray read 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.6. and <hi>chap.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 4.6.</p>
               <p>Fifthly: That the greateſt enemies that a people can have, are ſuch as would ſtrip them of the meanes they have of enjoying God. See what brake <hi>Ely's</hi> neck, and his Daughter in laws heart, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients made up the Churches bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Lamentations, <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.6, 7, 9. Thoſe are none of our friends who would
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169964:30"/>put us into ſo ſable a dreſſe, to mourn over the Funerals of our Religion: Or if you will needs ſay you are, we beſeech you expreſſe your friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to us ſome other way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>The ſecond Uſe, of Reproof to ſuch as place their happineſſe in the enjoyment of the world.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF our higheſt happineſſe be in the enjoyment of God, where ſhall we finde, or how ſhall we make a reproof ſharp enough for their folly who place it in the enjoyment of outward things? whether there be any ſuch or no, I ſhall no otherwiſe determine than by leaving every Reader to an application of theſe three things, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt: Doe we look ſo farre as, and no further than the world, in our thoughts, ſtudies, deſignes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then is the world our happineſſe: if we
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169964:30"/>thought it to be in any thing beyond it, we would look further; 'tis as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible not to be, as not to look every jot as far as we ſuppoſe any happineſſe may be found.</p>
               <p>Secondly: Doe we ſpend more of the ſtrength and ſpirits of our ſoul for the world than we doe for God? hath it, not the ordinary actings, but the intenſion and utmoſt vigour of our hearts? our operations ſtretched to the higheſt pin? <hi>ex. gr.</hi> the higheſt ſearch of our invention to finde out means to get it? the higheſt reach of our reaſon and judgement, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether this or that (ſuppoſe this ſin, or that duty) be the neareſt way to it? the exacteſt ſtrain of our diligence to act according to this pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent determination? Doe we move towards it with the ſtrength of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections? And be our feares and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies never ſo deep concerning any thing, as, leſt we ſhould miſcarry about it? doubtleſſe the mind would not be carried out at ſuch a rate, after any thing leſſe than a ſuppoſed happineſſe;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169964:31"/>where all our heart is, there is all our treaſure.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Are we wont to deliberate about owning of our God? whether it be ſafe, prudent, advantageous? but to be reſolute, and never put it to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, about proſecuting the things of the world? then aſſuredly is the world our utmoſt end; the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry top of our felicity, it never comes under debate whether that which is our laſt end ſhould be purſued, or no
<note n="*" place="margin">De fine non eſt aelibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum.</note>. If any of us be found in this predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Lord make us ſee our folly, to expreſſe it is not poſſible. Can any of theſe things here below make us happy? I ſhall call you out no further then experience. Is happineſſe</p>
               <p n="1">1. In Riches? I doe not remember you of their
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 8.14. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10.</note> thorns whilſt they ſtay; nor of their wings
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 23, 5.</note>, to be gone. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you may not forget him who had more wealth than he knew what to doe with, to have died a fool, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.17.20.</p>
               <p>In Pleaſures? which way then went <hi>Dives</hi> into that place of torments, <hi>Luke</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:169964:31"/>16.23.28? And what beaſt is it that may not be accounted happier than we?</p>
               <p n="3">3. In honours? no Engliſh man, I hope, is ſo ſimple as to beleeve it, who hath ſeen the fountain of it dropping its laſt upon a ſcaffold, and moſt of the veſſels fill'd by him, emptied into the duſt. If you labour for theſe things, or ought elſe of the like nature, you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for the wind, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.16. And to lay out for it time, ſtrength, ſpirits, wit, wiſdom, body and ſoul, muſt needs be a folly of the firſt magnitude.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:169964:32"/>
               <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>The third Uſe, of Exhortation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEaving then out of our hearts thoſe vain things that cannot profit us, let us be exhorted to fill them up with that which can, ſcorning to waſte our ſpirits about the enjoyments of the world where happineſſe is not, let us employ all our ſtrengthin labouring after the enjoyment of God, where it is, the more we can poſſeſſe of this, the more we have of heaven. 'Tis doubtleſſe our ſin as well as miſery, that we ſhould need any motives to ſuch a duty, indeed to ſuch a priviledge as this is; but becauſe we doe, I ſhall lay down this one, <hi>viZ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The tranſcendent excellency of this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment above all others, and that both in regard of</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The Object, God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>The Act, Fruition.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, in regard of the Object, God. In whom</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:169964:32"/> 1. There is nothing that is not ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and deſireable; whatever is not good, perfect, excellent, to be ſure that is not God. Divine beauty is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt, look upon the choiſeſt of the Creatures,
<note n="*" place="margin">Eſt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid quod ſe dedecuiſſe putes.</note> and if there be beauty, there be alſo blemiſhes; not ſo our God, you cannot attempt to deſcribe him, but removing from him all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection: If all beauty cannot draw out our ſouls, and melt them into ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent deſires of fruition, then nothing can.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is in God every thing that is good and lovely. Divine beauty is compleat and perfect, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the world for an affection to cloſe with, that is not in him: If it be Greatneſſe, and Power, and Glory, and Victory, and Majeſty, they are all his, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.11. If it be peace he is the very God of it, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. If it be wealth, the Heaven, <hi>even the Heavens are the Lords, Pſal.</hi> 115.16. If it be love, <hi>God is love,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.8. and what ever elſe you can imagine that is deſireable.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:169964:33"/> 3. Theſe and all perfections elſe are in God, in an unparralleld way of eminency, not of the ſieze they are in us; that one Volume contains more, then the ſeveral editions of all the creatures, that are under Heaven, or in it: what is ſcattered elſewhere is but a drop to this Ocean. We may ſpeak exceſſively of other things, but not of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Beauty that is in God, is permanent, 'tis everlaſting, not fade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and periſhing as the Creatures is, out of whoſe garden every day plucks a flower
<note n="*" place="margin">Florem decoris finguli carpunt dies.</note>. Yea, the Heavens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which for their preheminence of beauty, are called, <hi>praeſtantiſsimum Corpus,</hi> a moſt excellent piece indeed, and are by ſome ſuppoſed to conſiſt of
<note n="*" place="margin">Ex quintâ eſſentiâ.</note> a finer matter then any of the four Elements, which go to the making up of other beauties; even theſe glorious bodies ſhall wax old as doth a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 1.11. tis God only that hath immortalitie, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16. <hi>and in whom there is no variableneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:169964:33"/> 5. All the beauty and goodneſſe that is in the Creature, is of Gods putting there, and what ever is in the effect, is more eminent in the cauſ, how glorious is that Soveraign of the skies, the Sun, and that Queen of Heaven the Moon! There is beauty in the Heavens; how gallantly are they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpangled with Stars! Ther's beauty in the Earth, how finely is it embroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with fruits and flowers! There is beauty in men, women, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how much more is there in God that made them? that little that is in the channel doth many times extreemly raviſh us, and we are ſick of love till we can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it, what ſhould not that doe that is in the Fountain?
<note n="*" place="margin">Si ſic in creaturis labore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quid in ipſo Deo?</note> if the Creatures have ſo much, their maker cannot chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge leſs then all.</p>
               <p n="6">6. When we have ſaid and imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all that we can of the excellencie of God, when we are ſwallowed up and and have loſt our ſelves under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of it, we come infinitely ſhort of what is indeed in him.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nullus intellec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus poteſt deum cognoſcere ut cogn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcibilis, eſt Aq. par.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 12, <hi>Art.</hi> 7</note> God is in all his glorious perfections incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:169964:34"/>
               <p> Now truly if there be nothing in God that is not deſireable, nor a want of any thing that is; if what ever we dote upon in the Creature, be no more then a ſpark to that ſun, and that too, let down from that Father of Lights; if all the beauty and goodneſſe we can ſee in him, be ſhort of what indeed it is, and all that is, be everlaſting, to ſupply ſufficient matter for our delight and complacencie to all eternity; how excellent is the enjoyment, when this God ſhall be the Object of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In regard of the Act, Fruition, which (as we have ſeen already
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</note>) is a cleaving unto God by love, for his own ſake, as the choiceſt emanation of the ſoul, is love; ſo of all loves that which pitcheth upon God, which is then in its higheſt glory and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, when it carryes out the ſoul af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, for his own ſake; for the good that is in him, rather then the good that comes by him. This love hath moſt of excellency in it, whether you look upon.
<list>
                     <item>1. The kind of it.</item>
                     <item>2. The degree.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:169964:34"/>
               <p> Firſt, Its a love of a Nobler kind, flowing from higher principles, refin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thoſe dregs that lie at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of other loves. <hi>Ex. gr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. We may love God meerly becauſe he is able to do us good, having all in him, that is wanting in us. This is but <hi>Amor indigentiae,</hi> a neceſſitous love, and hath ſomething of ſelf in the compoſition of it, and we may</p>
               <p n="2">2. Love God meerly that he may do us good; This is <hi>Amor concupiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> a mercinary love, as like to theirs as it can look who followed Chriſt for loaves, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.26. and is not ſo much a love of God as of our ſelves, and we may</p>
               <p n="3">3. Love God becauſe he hath done us good, given us health, peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this at beſt is but <hi>Amor gratitudinis,</hi> a thankful love, and may eaſily flow even from a good nature; but the love that is in Fruition, is of another cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, when God is loved for himſelf. Then.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The deſires of the ſoul are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed out after him with a large wing,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169964:35"/>thirſting after him as a dry and parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed land for rain, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.1. and pant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after him as the chaſed heart for the brooks of water, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1. to whom ſhe thinks ſhe can never be near enough; and there is not any way of Communion that ſhe doth not ardent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly long to meet him in. To ſee him, and to gaze upon his beauty as long as ſhe lives, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. To hear him, his mouth is moſt ſweet, his lips are like Lillies, and every ſyllable is Myrrh that droppeth from them, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.13.16. To be in his arms, one hand muſt be under her head, and the other muſt embrace her, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.3. Yea, to be in his very heart, and to be ſet there as a ſeal, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6. Yea all the familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that God affords her here doe not ſatisfie; to be in the body is to be at too great a diſtance, and is upon that account a burden that ſhe groanes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. A diſſolution is lookt upon as far better, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. towards a fuller enjoyment of him, no pace will ſerve but the ſwifteſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8. <hi>ult.</hi> and her prayer is not onely <hi>Come Lord
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169964:35"/>Jeſus,</hi> but <hi>come quickly,</hi> Apoc. 22.20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where art thou Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Soliloq.</hi> cap. 1.</note>) <hi>why doeſt thou hide thy face?</hi> Perhaps thou wilt ſay, <hi>No man ſhall ſee me and live: Eia domine moriar, ut te videam,</hi> if that, Lord, be all, let me dye upon that condition. This now is <hi>amor unionis,</hi> a deſire of enjoying God as immediately as we may. When God is loved for himſelf, Then</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſoul is poſſeſſed with a full contentment in God, as portion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.6. She will ſee more in him than in all the world beſide, and there will reſt
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ama il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in quod ſunt omnia bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, &amp; ſufficit.</hi> Aug. <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual. c.</hi> 34</note> (ſee before <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.) this is <hi>amor complacentiae,</hi> a love made up of nothing but delight. And</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſoul will be inclined to all poſſible compliance with God, that love which tyes us to him for his own ſake, is an imperative affection, it will lay us at his feet, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7. it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver give us leave to ſay of any duty that God commands us, that it is either dangerous, ſee <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.18, 19. or
<note n="*" place="margin">Quid non cogit amor? ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus labor difficilis.</note> difficult, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.15. or tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<note place="margin">In eo quod a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur, aut non labor la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boratur aut ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note>, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.20. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.3. or unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169964:36"/>of ſo excellent a kinde is this love of God; 'tis <hi>amor amicitiae,</hi> a friendly love. And</p>
               <p>Secondly; for the degree of it, it is a raviſhment of ſpirit,
<note n="*" place="margin">Raptus ex intui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu divinae pulchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinis ortus.</note> even unto ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5. begotten by a contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of divine beauty; 'tis <hi>amor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebrians,</hi> prevailing upon the ſoul even to a ſpiritual drunkenneſſe; 'tis love intended to the uttermoſt, the higheſt ſtrain that the heart can reach unto: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things doth ſuch a ſoul think may be loved too much, but the meaſure by which ſhe loves God, is to love him without meaſure; 'tis love as hot as fire, not glowing a little in the aſhes, but affording moſt vehement flame, <hi>Can.</hi> 8.6. nay heat in fire may be put out by a little water; many waters can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not quench this, <hi>Can.</hi> 8.7. as it was ſaid of <hi>Laurence</hi> frying upon the Grid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iron
<note n="*" place="margin">Segnior fuit ignis, qui foris uſſit, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui intus accendit.</note>, <hi>The fire without was leſse than the flame within;</hi> 'tis a love that moves our bowels which an ordinary qualm of affection can never doe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.4. Such impreſſions can it make upon beleevers, when it is duly acted, who
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169964:36"/>doe bear about upon their ſoules (as <hi>Paul</hi> did in his body) the marks of the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.17. but we cannot yet give over ſo ſweet a theam, let me offer you a further taſt of its excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in theſe four particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God himſelf takes it into his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties, if it be not rather his very eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; <hi>God is love,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.8. and God is nothing but what is excellent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is the womb of all duties elſe which we owe to God, and 'twill bring them forth as occaſion ſhall be offered, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Domiue dilige, &amp; fac quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid vis.</note> ſaid to Chriſt, God doth freely ſay us, <hi>First love me, and then do what you will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. All our abilities, all our doings and ſufferings will finde no entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment above, unleſſe this love of God give them a certificate, that they came from her. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1, 2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. 'Tis ſomething that this will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to be a duty, when moſt duties elſe ſhall be obſolete, and out of date; they are practicable on earth, this in heaven. They have their time, this its eternity.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:169964:37"/>
               <p> Now if there be ſo much of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in the Object, God, and in the Act, Fruition, this is motive enough, if the Lord will vouchſafe to ſet it on, to aſpire after the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, above all the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments elſe that are under the Sunne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:169964:37"/>
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>Some brief Directions as to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Duty.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF the Saints would be as much in heaven as is here poſſible, and grow up more and more in this unſpeakable happineſſe of enjoying God, they muſt follow theſe directions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you muſt endeavour to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe your knowledge of God, and your acquaintance with thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies that he is cloath'd withall. Much of that time which you ſpend in the ſtudy of other things, will be very well worth the redemption to be laid out upon this.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Incog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum non poteſt amari.</hi> Aug.</note> What you doe not know, you cannot love, what you doe not love, you cannot ſo much as deſire to enjoy. There muſt be ſome appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the object before there can be any motion of the faculty toward it. See before <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Secondly, you muſt endeavour to get and maintain an aſſurance of your
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169964:38"/>intereſt in God; give all diligence to put this out of queſtion, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. If there be never ſo much beauty, goodneſſe, love, power, grace, holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in God, you can never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it, in caſe it be not, or you think it is not there for you. Fruition doth preſuppoſe propriety, and ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it. He that is in his ſins God will not own him, and he that is in Chriſt, and yet doubts it, will not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be perſwaded to own God; and be ſure to build your aſſurance upon good grounds. I have read of a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy man, that ſuppoſed all the Ships in ſuch a Haven to be his own
<note n="*" place="margin">Thraſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes naves in Pireum portum appella n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſuas eſſe.</hi>
                  </note>; and of a Gentlewoman in <hi>Mantua,</hi> who would not be perſwaded but that ſhe was married to a King
<note n="*" place="margin">Marcel. Donatus <hi>de hist. med. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>; as that poor man enjoyed thoſe veſſels which he had no title to an inch of, and that woman the husband whom ſhe never ſaw, ſo doe thoſe men God who have no intereſt in him but in a dream.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, abate of your deſires to enjoy other things. Love not the world; that is, Let not your hearts go
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169964:38"/>out immoderately after it; if any man doe ſo, the love of the Fathers is not in him, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.15. A River let out into many channels, muſt needs run the ſhallower in ſome. 'Tis grown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Proverb, that thoſe perſons who love over-many, are never wont to love over-much
<note n="*" place="margin">Alterius vires ſubtrahit alter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor.</note>. The love of God and of the world are like two buckets in a Well, while one goes up the other goes down. We muſt leak our hearts, and let out all that is too much of our love to the world, they will then be the better at leiſure to contemplate the beauty, and to be raviſht with the excellencies of our God. Shall we ſuffer any thing to be competitors for our hearts with him? What is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of a wife, a child, a friend, an eſtate, an office, a command, to the enjoyment of a God? Indeed what is any thing to him, before whom all the Nations of the world are leſſe than no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.17?</p>
               <p>Fourthly, walk cloſe with God; the nearer you walk up to him, the more you are like to enjoy of him. More particularly,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:169964:39"/> 1. Walk lovingly: Let all your doings be done in charity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.14. Let Gods love in your ſouls be as a weight in the ſcale
<note n="*" place="margin">Quod eſt pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brâ, hoc eſt amor in animâ.</note>, carrying all your deſignes its own way. Let this love be the poize of all your actions, and goe no other way but whither this ſhall lead you
<note n="*" place="margin">Amor meus pondus meum, illo feror, quocun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que feror.</note>. Draw out the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of this grace, as far upward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God as you are able. Love is a ſociable affection, it will carry you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the company of God, and bring him into yours; you are promiſed ſo much in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.23. <hi>If a man love me, my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Walk beleevingly: Keep your eye of Faith as open as you can; you have no way elſe of ſeeing him who is inviſible, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.27. Neither is God wont to dwell in our hearts but by faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. If this eye of our ſoul be ſhut or drowſie, we may ſay with <hi>Auguſtine, Mecum eras, &amp; non er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am tecum,</hi> God was with us, but we were not with him. We can have no converſe, even with thoſe friends that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169964:39"/>are about us, whilſt we are aſleep. In a word,</p>
               <p n="3">3. Walk holily: This is to walk with God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24. and to have our converſation in heaven, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. then is God moſt enjoyed, when a gracious life ſhall goe along an equal pace with a gracious heart; if the Saints cannot ſin themſelves out of Gods favour, yet they may out of his familiarity. How often in Scripture is peace, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and the enjoyment of God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed unto his people in a way of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? See <hi>Pſal,</hi> 50.23. <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8, 9. Pretend what you will you converſe but a little with God, who converſe much with ſin. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.6, 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:169964:40"/>
               <head>SECT. X. <hi>Of the enjoyment of God in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEcauſe the moſt ordinary way of Gods converſing with his Saints here in the body is by his Ordinances, as we have in part ſeen before <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. I ſhall enquire briefly into the cauſes why the Saints many times enjoy ſo little of God in them, that they may ſee and remove thoſe abatements of their felicity. Is it not</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe we doe not ſeek God in his Ordinances? but think we may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy as much of him any where elſe? To how many are the Ordinances of God as indifferent things? If once it become indifferent to men, whether they eat and drink, or not; no wonder if they find neither their palats pleas'd, nor their bodies nouriſhed.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>May not God be enjoyed, his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, love, and ſweetneſs taſted, out of Ordinances as well as in them?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:169964:40"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> If this may be, yet ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It be to be injoied by thoſe that neglect his Ordinances? What did the King do, when ſuch as were invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his feaſt made light of it, did he carry, or ſend his Proviſions after them, that they might fare as well at their Farms, and Merchandize, as at his Table? you will find it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if you read <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.7. Or,</p>
               <p n="2">2. It be ſo much of God as is wont to be injoyed when we meet him in his Ordinances? if it be, why have not the Saints been contented with it? ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. and 48.9. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> places that may better be taſted then explained. Or,</p>
               <p n="3">3. It be not rather a re-taſting, and relliſhing again of that ſweetneſſe and comfort which was left upon the Soul, when God in his Ordinances commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated himſelf unto us, a making good of that gracious promiſe of Chriſt, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26.</p>
               <p>Ob. <hi>But divers Saints that do conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe the Ordinances, do yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169964:41"/>how little of God, they injoy in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> This perhaps may be:</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe we do not ſeek God there; or not ſeek him principally, poſſibly we reſt too much in them, and do not ſend up our ſouls to God tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row them, we do not carry our hearts high enough, but are ready to take in ſatisfaction meerly from the work done, ſeeking that in the Ordinances, which we ſhall never find but in God. Let us rectifie this miſcarriage, we ſhall not undervalue the Ordinances to account them empty things unleſſe God fill them, Wells of Salvation, but no Water there for us, Breaſts of Conſolation, but Dry ones, no milk for us, unleſſe we can taſte and feed upon God in them; if we would injoy our God, we muſt be pleaſed with nothing, no not in the Sanctuary, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we can ſee our God, and our King walking there, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 68.24. Or,</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe we do not ſeek God in all his Ordinances; ſome Chriſtians are altogether for private Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169964:41"/>and do deſpiſe the publick; ſome for publick Ordinances, and neglect the private, if we will not meet God in one, can we expect that God ſhould meet us in another? if we neglect Chriſts company in the midſt of two or three in private, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.20. may he not walk in the midſt of the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks in publick, &amp; not ſuffer us to ſee him? <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.13. pray conſider that thoſe Saints who have ſought God in all his Ordinances, as their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, have found him in every one of them to their comfort, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.4. and 63.5, 6. <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4. Or,</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe we do not ſeek God there after a due order, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13. with that frame and temper of ſpirit, that preparation of Heart and Soul which is requiſite. Perhaps</p>
               <p n="1">1. Prepoſſeſſed, too full, and too wel ſatisfied with ſome thing elſe, now truly
<note n="*" place="margin">Intus existens prohibet alienum.</note>, if the Stomack be ful, though it be but with husks that the Swine do eat, it will taſte but little ſweetneſſe, even in that bread which is in our fathers houſe: Or</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:169964:42"/> 2. Without prayer, that God would let fall influences from himſelf, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row his Ordinances upon us, do not we know that God expects ſome imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as he is a God hearing prayers? <hi>Pſa.</hi> 65.2. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36, 37. <hi>We have not, becauſe we ask not, Jam.</hi> 4.2. can we expect, that God ſhould look upon thoſe that will not ſo much as ſpeak to him?</p>
               <p>This for the firſt part, our higheſt happineſſe is the injoyment of God, we muſt now conſider the quality of that injoyment.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:169964:42"/>
            <head>Part. II.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E have ſeen in general, that the higheſt Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Saints is the injoyment of God, it remains that we now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, what kind of injoyment it muſt be, in order whereunto we ſhall take into conſideration the</p>
            <div type="section">
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Propoſition. <hi>That injoyment of God which is the Saints higheſt Happineſſe, ſhall be immediate, ſole, free, full, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Each of which five particulars, I ſhal indeavour to prove and apply, as they lie in order.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:169964:43"/>
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>That our higheſt Happineſs ſhall bee to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy God immediately.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre below we injoy God by means, not ſo hereafter, not in Ordinances, graces, bleſſings, or through any ſuch <hi>Mediums,</hi> as we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy him now, all theſe, though they be great conducements to that happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which we are capable of on earth, they be yet great abatements of that, which we ſhall be crown'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in Heaven, to injoy a friend in his picture, letters, tokens, is ſhort of what we injoy, when we have his perſonal preſence; neither doth the Sun heat, or light us ſo comfortably through a cloud, as when the glorious body of it is open to us, without any interpoſition: our happineſſe in God will be without its perfection, till our injoyment of God, ſhall be without means
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deus ſine ullo mediatore aut medio cauſa im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediata erit—&amp; objectum immedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trae feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatis, Zanch. de nat. Dei. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note>. Let us conſider:</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:169964:43"/> 1. Chriſts Kingdom ſhal be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up, <hi>that God may bee all in all, (i. e.)</hi> all Ordinances, and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, which are means of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying God here, ſhall ceaſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, that we may be fully and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly happy,, Chriſt hath ſome things in his Kingdom, that bears an Analogy to the means and inſtruments of governing in the Kingdomes of men, and in each of them is God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyable. He hath his <hi>Militia</hi> and his laws, with promiſes and threatnings in the Ordinances of his Word; his Seals to confirm to his people, his free grants of priviledge, in the Ordinance of his Sacraments; his Embaſſadours and Offieers for the management of ſpiritual affairs in the Ordinance of his Miniſtry, the ceaſing of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is the ceſſation of all theſe, that God may immediately ſucceed to fill up the meaſure of our promiſed bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe to the full.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All Rule, and all Authority and Power muſt be put down, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. which (
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aqu. in locum Mr. Jo. Goodwins</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>p.</hi> 15.</note> divers expound of lawful
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169964:44"/>government, and) are remoter means of our injoying of God, by preſerving to us, and protecting us in the uſe of thoſe Ordinances which God appears in, and upon this account muſt even theſe be put down, <hi>That God may bee all in all,</hi> that is, That our happineſſe may be compleated.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To injoy God by means, is to know him but in part, and to ſee him in a glaſs darkly, <hi>in aenigmate,</hi> to have ſuch apprehenſions of God as we have of a Riddle, which we do not fully under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, but that degree of happineſſe which we ſhall be advanced to hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is to ſee him face to face, to injoy him immediately, and all this you have in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. and altogether as much, though in fewer words, in 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. that what we ſhall be in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and happineſſe, above what we are, wil be this, That we ſhal ſee God, as he is <hi>(i.e.)</hi> clearly and immediately
<note n="*" place="margin">Dioniſ. Carthuſ. in locum.</note>.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Was it not the higheſt pitch of happineſſe which the Apoſtles ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly groan'd after 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4.? and what was that but to be preſent with
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169964:44"/>the Lord, <hi>v.</hi> 8? why had not theſe Saints the preſence of God already? Sure they had in his graces and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and they had the earneſt of his ſpirit, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. they injoyed God by theſe means, 't was the injoyment of God without them, 't was his immediate preſence which they groan'd for; ſo <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. <hi>I deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better,</hi> were not <hi>Paul</hi> and Chriſt together al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready? Sure they were near, very near, one to another; ſee <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>I live, yet not I, but Christ liveth in me,</hi> &amp;c. he had the preſence of Chriſt by faith, and this was very good; his deſire to depart, was to have the preſence of Chriſt by ſight, to injoy him immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, this is far better.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:169964:45"/>
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>This Branch of the point improved by way of information.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT will follow from what we have now ſaid.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the injoyment of God by means, is but a little drop of that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of ſweetneſſe and ſatisfaction, which the Soul ſhall be filled with, when ſhe ſhall come to enjoy God without them. All the raviſhment of our ſpirits in prayer, hearing, medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is but a ſip of thoſe Rivers of it, which we ſhall have in Heaven, ſo that unſpeakable ſolace of our Souls meeting God in an Ordinance, may ſomething help us to gueſſe at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable bliſſe of a Soul meeting God in Heaven. Will you ſtay then a little, and ſee what it is to be in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven below, to injoy God by means and at a diſtance?</p>
               <p>If <hi>David</hi> look but upon the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary where God gave ſome evidences
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169964:45"/>of his preſence, hee is tranſported with apprehenſions of felicity in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, oh how amiable are thy Tabernacles, O Lord of Hoſts? and ſome ſuppoſe the latter part of the 3d. <hi>v.</hi> to be an abrupt expreſſion, not at all depending upon the fore going words, <hi>Thine Altars O Lord of Hoſts, my King, and my God,</hi> as men are wont to expreſs themſelves concerning any thing that they are raviſht withall, ſee alſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. and 43.3.</p>
               <p>If God in Ordinances be ſo deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo ſatisfying, ſo amiable, ſo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing; what ſhall God be without them? if the picture pleaſe ſo abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly what will the perſon do? if ſo much bliſſe be caſt upon the ſoul from a copy, what may we not expect from the original?</p>
               <p>The Saints here rejoice with joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable and full of glory 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. and yet doth this reſult but from our injoyment of God by the <hi>medium</hi> of Faith, the degrees that will be added unto it by viſion muſt needs render it inconceivable, and running over; if
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169964:46"/>ſome of the Saints here are ſo ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up of Divine ſweetneſſe, that they deſire God to forbear
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Xave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabat ſatis est, Domine ſatis eſt, nec enim mens mea in hâc vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ, tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gaudioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pondus capit. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferente. A Lapid. in Cant</hi> 2.3</note>, we can but (yea we cannot ſo much as) imagine what will be.</p>
               <p>The remembrance of God in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate meditation is ſweet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.34. and if a gracious Soul can entertain her ſelf with ſome conferences with her God, <hi>ſhe is ſatisfied as with marrow and fatneſſe, Pſal.</hi> 63.5, 6. our entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments below are a great feaſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.16, they are promiſed us as ſuch, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.6. we are invited to them as ſuch, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.5. they are fed upon as ſuch, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 34.8. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.103. we are cheered up at them as at a feaſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1. can a created un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding gueſſe, what ſhal be provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for us above?</p>
               <p>In Gods Kingdome of grace we are made to drink of the Rivers of his pleaſures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8. but when God ſhall immediately poſſeſſe the Soul, and fill it; when the Soul ſhall imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately poſſeſſe God, and be full of him; when this Kingdom of grace
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169964:46"/>ſhall expire, and all the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it (as ſo many Eclipſes of our happineſſe) ſhall vaniſh away, ſhall we not then drink of the Fountain? ſurely feaſts, and ſweetneſſe, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and fatneſſe, are terms exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too diminutive to give us any more then a ſmall hint, of that incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That when the happineſſe of the Saints is at higheſt, then will be the time, when they ſhall be above any need of Ordinances, when you ſhall enjoy God immediately, then you ſhal have no need of means to enjoy him by; and when you ſhall ſo enjoy God, you ſhall be perfectly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>If any would vouchſafe to read this who pretend to the injoyment of God, and yet deny it to bee in the uſe of means; I would adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to argue the caſe with them thus. If you do indeed injoy God at all, it is immediately, and ſuch as ſo injoy him are perfectly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and are you of that number?
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169964:47"/>is every evill removed? have you never any pain, ſorrow, affliction, ſin? is every deſire ſatisfied? do your appetites go out after nothing in the World? no body will beleeve it, and ſo you are not yet fully bleſſed and happy, whatever you may be, and by conſequence your immediate injoyment of God, is but the injoyment of a fancy.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle tells us, that now <hi>(i. e.)</hi> in this life, if wee ſee God at all, it is in a glaſſe, wee have need of ſuch <hi>mediums</hi> to do it by; the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate viſion of him face to face is reſerved for hereafter <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the life that is to come, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</p>
               <p>Adde hereunto, that if you injoy God here immediately, you ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy him, as you ſhall hereafter, and ſo not onely your preſent, but your future condition is apparent, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears what you ſhall be, as well as what you are: and, how then is it poſſible you ſhould be accounted of their number, who are now the ſons
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169964:47"/>of God, but it doth not yet appear what they ſhall be, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>A further Improvement of the point by way of exhortation, againſt the fear of Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOu ſee that it muſt be an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate injoyment of God, that can let us in to the fulneſſe of our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Let us hence be exhorted ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deſire Death, then to be afraid of it, if the end be deſirable, why ſhould the means be dreadfull? to be happy is to injoy God immediately, which we ſhal never do except we die: There ſhall no man ſee God and live, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.20. we ſhall not indeed ſee him till we be like him, 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.2. nor be like him enough to ſee him, till we be ſinleſſe, nor be ſo, whileſt we are alive, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.20. God as a found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, muſt melt us before we ſhall be
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169964:48"/>ſufficiently refin'd to come ſo neare him, and the Furnace he wil do it in, is Death. God pardons our ſin by the death of Chriſt, but totally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroies it by our own: we die in ſin, and to ſin by a metaphorical death, but we onely die from it, by a natural one, and this muſt be done, its not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that ſin be totally pardoned, that it have no guilt, it muſt be totally aboliſhed, that it have no being, before we ſhal be meet enough to bee parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the inheritance of the Saints in light.</p>
               <p>As Death deſtroies the being of our nature, ſo 't is exceeding formidable, and the King of terrours: but as it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroies the being of our ſin, to let us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſence of our God 't is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly deſirable. <hi>Socrates</hi> profeſſed himſelf willing to die upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that he might enjoy thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies that went before him, as <hi>Orphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Heſiod, Homer, &amp;c.</hi> our incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, we ſhal come to enjoy our God, after this the Apoſtles groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed earneſtly, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2.8. and if
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169964:48"/>Chriſt ſay, ſurely I come quickly; the ſpouſe wil anſwer, even ſo come Lord Jeſus. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.20. We ſhould not be afraid of our paſſage into the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate imbracements of our God, which we then enter upon, when into his hands we commend our ſpirits; fleſh and bloud cannot inherit the Kingdom of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.50. wee could not be happy, if we were not mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:169964:49"/>
               <head>SECT. IIII. <hi>That our perfect Happineſſe ſhall be in the ſole injoyment of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat ever others may ſuppoſe, we cannot but place our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe when it ſhal be at the full, in the injoyment of God alone, exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the injoyment of every thing elſe. Here below the Saints have their God, and this is their happineſſe; but they have withal ſomething elſe, Wives, Children, Friends, Houſes, Money, Lands, Honours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this is a diminution of their happineſſe, it wil never be at higheſt til they ſhal injoy God alone, God and nothing elſe. Let us conſider:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The phraſe of the Text: <hi>God ſhall be all,</hi> we ſhal have nothing elſe: Himſelf
<note n="*" place="margin">Premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis erit, qui vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> ſhal be our exceeding great reward, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. our draughts of Happineſſe ſhal be taken in immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from the Fountain, and not be
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169964:49"/>leſſened by their conveyance to us in any channel.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Then cometh the end, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. which is expounded of
<note n="*" place="margin">Ego pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum de fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne mundi Piſcat. Schol. in locum.</note> the end of the World, there ſhal be an end of all the accommodations this world was wont to afford, nothing ſhal remain that a heart may be ſet upon. When ſhal this be?
<note n="*" place="margin">Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectione completâ Carthuſ. in loc.</note> When the Saints are entring upon the conſummation of their bleſſedneſſe. And why ſhal this be? Why ſhal there bee an end of whatever might be an object of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the whole Creation? You are anſwered in the Text; then commeth the end, that <hi>God may be all in all,</hi> that we may be fully happy in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God alone.</p>
               <p n="3">3, As all our happineſſe is in injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo much of our injoyment is by love, as we have noted already [<hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.] ſo that the leſſe we love God, the leſſe we injoy him, and as long as we have any thing beſide God wil not ſome of our love go out after it? ſo that what I aim at is eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; we ſhal not be perfectly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169964:50"/>til we perfectly injoy God, nor perfectly injoy him, til we perfectly love him, nor perfectly love him, til we have nothing to love elſe. So it is the ſole injoyment of God, which our Happineſſe when it is at the higheſt, ſhal conſiſt in. And I think.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This was <hi>Davids</hi> meaning in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.25. <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee?</hi> he had in the former verſe, expreſſed his confidence of Gods receiving him to glory, in this he declares what the glory was that he thirſted after, it was the ſole injoyment of God, God alone, and nothing elſe, and indeed, though while our love hath its infirmities, it hath other objects, yet
<note n="*" place="margin">Perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ſolum fitit quod ſummum eſt, Bern.</note> when it ſhal be perfectly healed, it wil pitch upon nothing but God alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:169964:50"/>
               <head>SECT. V. 1 <hi>Uſe of this Branch, by way of Exhortation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>J Have ſome thing from the laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned part of the propoſition to commend unto you by way of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, I ſhal beſeech you but to ſuffer theſe 4 words.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Learn in whatſoever ſtate you are, therewith to be content, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.11. we ſhould never grumble at any diſpenſations of our God, were we not guilty of ſome miſtakes about the matter of our Happineſſe; are you in a mean condition, and have you but a little of the world? be contented, you muſt have leſſe, you muſt have none; before ever you wil be happy.</p>
               <p>You have not that Eſtate, Honour, Credit, greatneſſe in the world which others have; and you whine, and ſigh, and take on, and repine, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur: what ails you? are theſe things
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169964:51"/>your happineſſe? nay, can you ever be truly happy, whileſt you have any one piece of them? is not your bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe alone in God? why then ſhould it diſcontent you to want ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſeeing you wil never be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as long as you have any thing? you wil never have enough, till <hi>God ſhall be all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Let your Converſation be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Covetouſneſſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. are you thirſty, immoderately thirſty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more and more of the earth? how fooliſh is ſuch an appetite; the more we enjoy beſide God, at the greater diſtance we ſtand from happineſſe. What ground have we for an inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſire of ſuch things, which we cannot poſſeſſe but upon condition of being miſerable? it is an un-Saint-like folly to graſp after much of the world, as if we could not be wel without it, when we know it is impoſſible for us to be wel enough with it; even God himſelf in conjunction with other things is not enough, it muſt be God alone that can fully bleſſe us: God in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169964:51"/>the creature (I deſire to ſpeak it with reverence) is an inconſiderable enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in compariſon of God in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If Riches increaſe, ſet not your hearts upon them, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 62.10. carry a holy jealouſie over your ſouls, leſt you cleave to them with a bird-lim'd affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Beg God to keep your hearts looſe enough, the world is a ſea, and every luſt is a Tempeſt ſtrong enough to ſink us, unleſſe Chriſt enable us (with <hi>Peter</hi>) to walk on top of it; this we muſt do, or we ſhal be miſerable: the more we love other things the leſſe we have of happineſſe, becauſe the more ſolely we love God, the more ſolely we enjoy him: the heart can have but a ſlender communion with him, if it be too much taken up with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther company; he can but by halfs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy his wife and children, who is daily troubled with the entertainment of ſtrangers.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In your patience poſſeſſe ye your ſouls, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.19. whatever loſſes wee meet with in the World it is our
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169964:52"/>folly, and our ſin, that if we looſe our friends or our goods, we have much adoe to keep our ſelves, as if we had never heard of the patience of <hi>Job;</hi> when a ſtroak is directed but to our goods, we are ſimple enough to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect it upon our ſelves; like the Iriſh, who if they have a good Scymiter, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then their weapon ſhal be hurt, wil receive the blow upon their arm
<note n="*" place="margin">Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bern. hiſt.</note>. This folly would bee cured, if wee would be perſwaded, that we ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be happy till we have loſt all, till we have no friend no eſtates, no enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but God alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:169964:52"/>
               <head>SECT. VI. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                  <hi>Uſe of this ſame point by way of Inſtruction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF our higheſt happineſſe be the ſole enjoyment of God, we may take out ſome leſſons thence for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; theſe that follow ſeem to be very legible.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it is an impoſſibility to make the Saints of God miſerable; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is impoſſible to deprive them of their God, in whom alone is all their happineſs. They may loſe</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Their Liberty,</hi> as <hi>Joſeph, Peter, Paul, Silas, &amp;c.</hi> the primitive Chriſtians, by the Heathen perſecutors
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceres con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecti fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, locis tenebroſis, &amp;c. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>, and the Orthodox by the <hi>Arrians</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. hiſt. Eccleſ. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note>, Chriſt himſelf may be impriſoned, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.43. and <hi>Satan</hi> may make the <hi>mittimus, Apoc.</hi> 2.10. but this is not their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, this is not the glorious liberty of the ſons of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21. their God wil be in priſon with them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.23.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:169964:53"/> 2. <hi>Their Eſtates,</hi> they may ſuffer the ſpoiling of their goods, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. of a great part, or all, as it ſhal pleaſe their more potent enemies, of which we have examples
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. Hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>Euſeb. de vita Conſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 45.</note> enough in the Hiſtory of the Church, but this is not their happineſſe, they have in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a better and a more enduring ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Their Lives,</hi> as the noble Army of Martyrs did. But this is not their happineſſe, they may ſav to the prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of their perſecutors
<note n="*" place="margin">Occide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quidem poteſtis, nocere non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtis.</note>, <hi>you may kill us, but it is not in your power to hurt us;</hi> they have a life which is hid with Chriſt in God, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3.</p>
               <p>Our happineſſe is not in any thing that the gates of Hell can reach unto; 'tis in God onely and ſolely, and who can take away our God from us? what condition can leave us without him? pray ask the Apoſtle in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35.38, 39.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. That (did wee rightly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it) the leſſe wee have of the world, the more wee may have of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, this I doubt wil ſeem a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169964:53"/>to moſt, but yet before you be too peremptory in concluding it ſo, conſider if happineſſe conſiſt in the ſole enjoyment of God; doth it not follow that the more ſolely wee enjoy him, the happier we are? and may we not the better ſo enjoy God, the leſſe we have to enjoy beſide him? even the troubles of a family do ſo far un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſſe us, that they hardly give us leave to attend upon the Lord without diſtraction, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.35. what then have they leave to do, who are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with more then this a thouſand fold?</p>
               <p>Are there none of us, whoſe poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and imployments in the world are more then they were wont to be? it would be wel to conſider (if we have ſo much leiſure) whether our enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God be not ſo much the leſſe; whether a great part of that time, and thoſe meditations which we were wont to lay out upon God, be not now wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and caſt away upon other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>You that have but a little to do with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169964:54"/>the world, pray make much of that condition, 't is your own fault if you have not the more to do with God; you have little elſe to take up your hearts, God may dwel and walk in them without diſturbance. God and you may be together a great part of your time, and the ſweetneſſe of your communion not hindred, whileſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are caſting up their accounts, you have leiſure enough to ſay with <hi>David,</hi> how precious are thy thoughts unto me O God, how great is the ſumme of them; if I ſhould count them, they are more in number then the ſands! <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139.17, 18. Whileſt others are follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſuits at a Court of Juſtice, you may follow all you have at a Throne of grace: whileſt others are numbring their flocks and heards, al your Arithmetick may be imploied to number your daies: whileſt others can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get out of the clutches of the world, you may get into the imbrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your God: you may bee in heaven whileſt others cannot ſee it for the interpoſition of too much earth.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169964:54"/>Truly a mean condition ſeems to bee capable of more happineſſe, then that which over-loadeth us with outward things.</p>
               <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. That little cauſe have the Saints to be troubled at the diſſolution of al things: That al theſe things here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſhal be diſſolved, he cannot doubt that is a Chriſtian, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. and the diſſolution of them ſhal be by fire, the Elements ſhal melt with fervent heat, the Earth alſo and the works that are therein ſhal be burnt up, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. that glorious heaven which rouls over our heads, ſhal be rouled together as a Scrowl; and al their Hoſt ſhal fal down, as the Leaf falleth off from the Vine, and as a falling Figge from the Fig-tree, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.4. and the earth under our feet the mother of ſo many good things, with her whole off-ſpring ſhal flee away, neither ſhal any place be found for her, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 20.11. it moves our bowels to behold the rage of fire in ſome petty deſolations; it wil you wil ſay be a melancholly proſpect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, to ſee it bury the whole world in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169964:55"/>its own aſhes. Wel, ſuppoſe we ſhould be of thoſe, who ſhal be found alive at the laſt day; ſhould it trouble or pity us that ſuch a world as this ſhould bee deſtroyed? ſure not a jot; unleſſe we would continue to our prejudice: for this end muſt come, <hi>That God may bee all in all,</hi> that there may bee nothing for us but God, that is, that we may be perfectly happy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:169964:55"/>
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>Shewing our happineſs to conſtſt in the free enjoyment of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS our happineſſe in the height and perfection of it, ſhal be to enjoy God immediately without helps, and ſolely without partners, ſo it wil be as neceſſary that wee enjoy him freely, without interruption or oppoſition: Here ſin ſtands in our way with power and pollution, and <hi>Satan</hi> with his fiery darts, and the world meets us with a thouſand contradictions, and whatever ſtands in the way of our enjoyment, ſtands in the way of our happineſſe, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> wil not bee perfect til al theſe impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be removed. Let us conſider</p>
               <p n="1">1. All enemies ſhal be ſubdued, <hi>v.</hi> 25, 26. <hi>Satan</hi> and ſin amongſt the reſt, which are the great diſturbers of our enjoyment of God, theſe ſhal trouble us no more; and the end is, <hi>That God may be all in all,</hi> that we may enjoy him freely without any contradiction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It follows rationally that if our
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169964:56"/>enjoyment of God be not free, our happineſſe in God cannot be ful: eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſturbance of enjoyment is an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of happineſſe; every evil is not excluded, where there is any thing left ſtanding between God and us, nor every deſire ſatisfied, when one great deſire is to have theſe rubs out of our way: we are ſo far from perfect happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as long as <hi>Satan,</hi> or ſin, or any thing ſhal thwart us in our enjoyment of God, that we are indeed miſerable and wretched men; and ſuch an appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion I think the Apoſtle had of this condition, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:169964:56"/>
               <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>A threefold uſe of this Point.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF we ſhall not be fully happy, till we ſhall enjoy God freely, and have nothing to oppoſe, or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt us</p>
               <p>Firſt, It will inform us, that in caſe our ſins ſhould go up to Heaven with us, we ſhould never be happy, becauſe we ſhould not be able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy God freely: here they croſs us, and do ever and anon interrupt our Communion, and would they not think you, do ſo there too? ſo thoſe carnal perſons that pray for Heaven, and yet would not part with their ſins, do (like the ſons of <hi>Zebedee</hi>) ask they know not what. To be in Heaven is to enjoy God
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vita ubi non eſt adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnans ubi nulla peccati il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecebra, &amp;c. Aug. meditat. c.</hi> 22.</note> freely, which neither the guilt of ſin, nor the pollution of it, will ſuffer us to do.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. This doth teach us what courſe to take, if we mean to be as much in Heaven, as it is poſſible to be here up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169964:57"/>earth: we muſt enjoy our God with all poſſible freedom. If you ask how ſhal this be done? pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what you would do to enjoy a friend freely, from whoſe ſociety you fetch much of your delight, would you not get your ſelf and your friend together? and exclude all other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany? and in caſe of intruſion, would you not refuſe to admit them? pray try ('tis a Noble experiment) if ſuch a courſe wil not bleſs your ſpirits with a more free enjoyment of God, then you do ordinarily attain unto.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You muſt get God and your ſouls together, by walking with him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24. and converſing in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. by ſending up your faith and love, and bringing God into your hearts, to ſup and walk, and dwel there: that you may look upon him, and hear him, and ſpeak to him and throw your ſelves into his Armes, and ſolace your ſouls in his Boſome as your God: when you ſtand, ſtand faſt in the Lord, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.1. When you walk, let it be in Gods waies,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169964:57"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.1. When you ſit down, let it be under his ſhadow, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3. When he invites you go with him into his Banqueting houſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.4. and eat and drink abundantly, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1. open your
<note n="*" place="margin">Os cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dica im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plet buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cella, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitatem animae ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Deus. Lor. in locum.</note> mouths wide, that he may fil them (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.10.) with what ever his preſence of grace brings with it, to feaſt your ſouls. But if you mean to do this freely, you muſt</p>
               <p n="2">2. Exclude all other company, every care that is ſuperfluous, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thought that is carnal muſt be ſhut out of doors. When <hi>Joſeph</hi> meant to diſcover himſelf to his Brethren, he cryed, <hi>Cauſe every man to go out from me, Gen.</hi> 45.1. When <hi>Abraham</hi> went to ſacrifice his Son, he ſaid to his young men, <hi>abide you here with the Aſs, and I and the Lad will go younder and worſhip, Gen.</hi> 22.5. <hi>Joſeph</hi> could not have unbowel'd himſelf freely, nor <hi>Abraham</hi> have met God in the Mount without interruption, had they not diſmiſſed their company: ſo muſt we deal with all other buſineſſes of the heart, cauſe every one of them to goe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169964:58"/>out from us, and abide behinde, if we would converſe with God freely, The cares of the world, and the luſts of our hearts are obſtreperous and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent, they wil keep ſuch a noyſe in our ſouls, that ſhal looſe very much of that communion with God, which we come together for; they wil pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide us ſuch avocations and diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that a great deal of our heart, which is al too little to be ſpent upon God, wil go out upon theſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If they offer to intrude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves again, when God and the ſoul are in communication, you muſt by no means admit them. Carnal luſts are ſufficiently ſawcy and immodeſt, they have impudency enough to thruſt themſelves into the ſoul, though ſhe be never ſo private and never ſo buſie in the company of her God: one errand or another wil they pretend, and be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate for audience if you give them admiſſion, you are ſadly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. And becauſe do what we can, theſe impediments wil be, and wil more or leſs diſturb us while we are here. It is</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:169964:58"/> 3<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>. Matter of comfort to the Saints, that when their happineſs ſhal be perfect, their enjoyment of God ſhal be free, without any diſturbance at all: every enemy ſhal be ſubdued:
<note place="margin">Beatum nihil quod non caret peccato. Ambr.</note> when we ſhal ſtand before the Lord in in Heaven, we ſhal have no Satan at our right hand to reſiſt us, his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting chains wil eternally keep him at a ſufficient diſtance; neither ſhal one of the luſts that haunt us here go along with us: it wil be a world where dwells nothing but righteouſneſs, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:169964:59"/>
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>Our full happineſs is in the full en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Fruition of God without means, or partners, or oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though it amount to very much of our felicity; yet not to all, it muſt be ful too without any defect: not as if the ſoul which is finite, could take in the whole Eſſence of God which is infinite, and ſo incomprehenſible; but the ſoul ſhal and muſt be ſo ful of God, as that it ſhal not be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive or deſire a jot more. Let's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the difference between our enjoyment of God here and hereafter, is but in degrees. Here it is inits infancy
<note n="*" place="margin">Gratia eſt aetas infantilis gloriae.</note> there it ſhal be in its ful age: Here it is in drops, there it ſhal be in the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Here tis
<note n="*" place="margin">per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis tranſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untis.</note> as light is in the Air there it ſhal be as
<note n="*" place="margin">Per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manentis</note> light is in the body of the Sun: Here we ſee Gods back parts, there we ſhal ſee his Face, not
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169964:59"/>his ſecond face (as ſome diſtinguiſh) which is grace and favour enjoyed by faith, but his firſt face which is, his divine Eſſence enjoyed by ſight: it is the ſame love whereby we cleave to God here and in Heaven (love never faileth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8) onely here it is love militant againſt
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas in preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti vitâ, infermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati non cedat, in futurâ infermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem non habeat, &amp; nunc re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetur iuvamine medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis tunc fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine ſanitatis Fulgent. l.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 8</note> many weakneſſes, there it ſhal be love triumphant over al. And God loves us with the ſame love now, which he wil love us with in Heaven; onely here it is but upon its deſign, there it wil be in Execution. In a word, the Apoſtle ſets down the difference of our enjoying God here and hereafter to be in this, <hi>That now it is but in part, and then it ſhall be at full,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As long as our enjoyment of God is not at ful; we are capable of more, and as long as we poſſeſs more we can deſire more, and ſo our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs is not perfected, becauſe every deſire is not ſatisfied.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:169964:60"/>
               <head>SECT. X. <hi>The Uſes of this Branch for Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and comfort.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt we may from what we laſt ſaid, be informed, that the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt ſight we can have of God out of Heaven is that ſight of him which we have in the Goſpel, becauſe it is the fulleſt. God is ſeen</p>
               <p n="1">1. In his creatures. Here (at leaſt) his eternal power and Godhead are le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibile enough, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In his Law, we cannot but ſee his Soveraignty, his Holineſs, and and his Juſtice, if we look here. But</p>
               <p n="3">3. In his Goſpel: our ſight of God is much fuller. Here we ſee
<list>
                     <item>1. More of this.</item>
                     <item>2. More then this.</item>
                     <item>3. More clearly.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, More of this, then ever was ſeen before. I ſhal inſtance in theſe Particulars, <hi>viz,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. More of Gods Power. Much
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169964:60"/>of this, very much was evidenced in making the world, having nothing but nothing to do it withal. Put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the whole <hi>Poſſe</hi> of men and Angels, and allow them no preexiſtent matter, and ſee if they be able to make ſo much as one hair. To enlarge here were to ſuppoſe my Readers ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worſe then not chriſtened: onely thus, <hi>I will praiſe thee</hi> (O Lord) <hi>for I am fearfully and wonderfully made: mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous are thy works and that my ſoul kuoweth right well,</hi> Pſal. 139.14.</p>
               <p>But is there not more of Gods pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er diſcovered in the Goſpel? to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don a ſinner is an act of great power, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.17, 18, 19. To quicken him, is an act of exceeding great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19. compared with chap. 2.1. The
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio impii ſit opus miraculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum? Aq. 1ae 2ae q.</hi> 113. <hi>Art.</hi> 10.</note> Schoolmen do enquire, whether the Juſtification of a ſinner be a miracle or no? a Queſtion that could not proceed but from an appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of ſome, more then ordinary, evidences of Gods power in this work. But what ſhal we think of the uniting of God and man in one perſon to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169964:61"/>bring this to paſs? I ſhal not ſo much as endeavour to puzle you, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring into the myſteries that are in it.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Aq</hi> 3. <hi>part q.</hi> 1.2.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> If you ſtudy how little you are able to
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>O admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabila myſteriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>! O inenr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabile co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercium<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Aug. me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditat c.</hi> 16.</note> apprehend of it you wil confeſs a longer manifeſtation of power in this one act to redeem the world, then was put forth at firſt to make it. And where is this diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but in the Goſpel?</p>
               <p n="2">2. More of Gods Wiſdom, whoſe deſign is to be advanced in the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinners. Now ſet aſide the Goſpel, and let al the men in the world and al the Angels in Heaven, lay their heads together, and tel you (if they can) by what means this ſhal be brought to paſs, they are ſinners that muſt be ſaved; this indeed wil ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Gods mercy, but what then ſhal become of his Juſtice? One At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute of God muſt not go down, whileſt another is ſet up, this were not for God to advance his whole ſelf. There is no imaginable way for Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to ſatisfie it ſelf, but either upon the ſinner himſelf, or upon ſome other
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:169964:61"/>in his ſtead, if upon themſelves the deſign is loſt, it muſt pay ſin its wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and ſo the ſinner periſheth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. if upon ſome other, who ſhould that be? if but a man, he cannot ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie; if a God, he cannot ſuffer; if ſinful he muſt ſuffer for himſelf; if ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe where ſhal ſuch a one be found? if willing how ſhould he be able? if not willing how were it juſt to lay it upon him?</p>
               <p>'Tis the Goſpel that unriddles all this, and in doing ſo diſcovers an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible wiſdom: hence are we told of this contrivement to ſave ſinners, that it is, the wiſdom of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. a wiſdom that no natural or moral helps, or parts, can raiſe us to the comprehenſion of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. wiſdom in a myſtery, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. A great myſtery, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. a myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery which the Angels deſire to look into, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. a diſcovery of the manifold wiſdom of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.10. there is more of this attribute opened in the Goſpel, then in that immenſe volume the whole world. But one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance more</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:169964:62"/> 3. More of Gods Juſtice, much of this was ſet on work in not ſparing the Angels that ſinned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. do not they ſeem to ſuffer the ſeverity of Gods juſtice, who (for ought we read) ſinned but once, and are yet under an eternity of wrath, without hope or means or poſſibility of reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? and it was much of juſtice that fel upon the old world, in ſo dreadful a ſhowre, that <hi>All in whoſe noſtrils was the breath of life</hi> periſhed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.22. and upon <hi>Sodom</hi> read, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.24, 25. and upon <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, read <hi>Num.</hi> 16.32, 33.</p>
               <p>But yet we have a manifeſtation in the Goſpel of more juſtice then al this, here we have God not ſparing his own ſon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. his onely ſon, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. the ſon of his love, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. the ſon of his boſome, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.18. though he did no ſin, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22. though he fulfilled all righteouſneſſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.15. yet having taken our ſins upon him, he did not ſpare him though he offered up prayers and ſupplications, with ſtrong crying and tears, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:169964:62"/>
               <p> Secondly in the Goſpel we ſee more then this; that is, what neither the book of the creatures, nor of the law did ever diſcover unto us: you may look elſe where in vain; but look into the Goſpel, you ſhal ſee God in Chriſt reconciling the world unto himſelf not imputing their treſpaſſes unto them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. quickning ſuch as are dead in treſpaſſes and ſins <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1. bringing life and immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to light, and offering it to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of ſinners, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.26. here we ſee a free grace, a full Chriſt, a general pardon, a way fot ſinful creatures to the injoyment of a juſt and holy God. The Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, were not by way of eminency to be called by that name
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Chemnit. loc. com. part</hi> 2. <hi>edit.</hi> 1594 <hi>in</hi> 4 <hi>to fol.</hi> 242.</note>, were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing elſe able to bring us glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of theſe good things.</p>
               <p>Thirdly what we ſee of God in the Goſpel, we ſee more clearly, then we can ſee it any where elſe, here below; and are therefore ſaid to behold his glory with open face as in a glaſſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. that the Jews under the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169964:63"/>adminiſtration of <hi>Moſes</hi> had a clearer diſcovery of God, then the Gentiles (who ſaw him but in his works) is not to be doubted: and how much clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ours is under the adminiſtration of the Goſpel, then theirs was under <hi>Moſes,</hi> is that we have produced the Apoſtle for. It is as much clearer, as the ſeeing of an object with open face in a glaſſe, is a clearer viſion then to look upon it, but thorow a vail: no picture can repreſent a thing ſo lively as a glaſſe doth. So the happieſt ſight of God out of heaven, is to ſee him in the Goſpel, becauſe it is the fulleſt. I hope men wil take heed how they carry themſelves to ſuch a Goſpel as this is, and I wil anon ſpeak with them about it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It is comfort for the Saints that their higheſt happineſſe ſhal be in the ful injoyment of God, your hungrings and thirſtings after more of him, ſhal one day end in a compleat ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, you ſhal have as much of him as your ſouls can hold here, it is much of your happineſſe, to have ſome
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169964:63"/>glimpſes of his glory ſhining upon you, and ſome drops of his favour di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled into your hearts: hereafter it ſhal be all your happineſſe to have it poured in til you ſhal be able to receive no more; and becauſe all your Lords joy cannot enter into you, to be ſure of having enough you ſhal enter into it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>v.</hi> 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:169964:64"/>
               <head>SECT. XI. <hi>That the enjoyment of God in which our highest happineſſe ſhall conſiſt is to be everlaſting.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL that we have ſaid of the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, though it riſe to very much, yet were it of any ſhorter date then eternity, it would not be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for an abſolute bleſſedneſſe. He ce</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Scriptures do every where expreſſe it to be everlaſting and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. <hi>We ſhall be ever with the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>and the pleaſures at his right hand are for evermore, Pſal.</hi> 16.11. <hi>our weight of glory ſhall be eternall,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. and our inheritance incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, which fadeth not away, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. and you know it is called life eternal and everlaſting, in a multitude of Scriptures.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Were it any thing ſhort of this, two things would prove it ſhort of its perfection.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:169964:64"/>
               <p> Firſt, There would be a poſſibility of being one time or another miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſo every deſire would not be ſatisfied. Miſery, ſet it at what diſtance you wil, is not onely what we do not deſire to come under, but what we cannot
<note n="*" place="margin">Miſeri eſſe non ſolum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumus, ſed nequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Aug.</note>.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> There were then ſome places for fear, and ſo for pain, 1 <hi>Joh,</hi> 4.18. and conſequently for evil, and that condition is not perfectly happy, which is capable of this, for every evil is not excluded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:169964:65"/>
               <head>SECT. XII. <hi>This briefly applied by way of exhortation and comfort.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WEE have ſeen the immediate injoyment of God, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing may ſhadow our happineſſe: the ſole injoyment of God; that nothing may abate it: the free injoyment of God; that nothing interrupt it, wee have ſeen it ſo full, that there is no room for more; and yet all this muſt and ſhal be eternal too, that we may
<note n="*" place="margin">Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo non eſt de eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur. Aug.</note> never ſee the expiration of it. And ſhal we not hence</p>
               <p n="1">1. Be exhorted, not to place our happineſſe in any thing that ſhal have an end? and (not to nauſeate you with particulars) ſuch are all that our eyes behold here below, the things that are ſeen are temporal, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. were there no other inſufficiency in them, yet would this prove their injoyment infinitely ſhort of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169964:65"/>that they can bee injoyed but for a time, and upon this account the Apoſtles did not think them worth the looking upon, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. what a fool was he, that comforted his ſoul with goods laid up in ſtore for many years? <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.19. it ſeems the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God himſelf would not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to an abſolute beatitude, were it not everlaſting; how much leſſe the enjoyment of the creature, which to the happieſt man under the ſun, cannot be above a ſpan long, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is not here comfort for the Saints, in all their afflictions? theſe can be ſuffered but for a time, God ſhal be enjoyed to all eternity, are we a while groaning under a burthen of ſin? <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. <hi>we ſhall be loaded with an eternal weight of glory,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. have we a ſpirit ful of wounds for a time? <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.14. we ſhal have a ſoul ful of God, for an eternity. Doth God forſake us for a ſmal moment, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.7. <hi>We ſhall be ever with the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ,</hi> 4.17. <hi>Doth heavineſs endure for a night? Pſal.</hi> 30.5. joy ſhal come
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169964:66"/>in a morning that hath no night at all, have we paines ever and anon? <hi>Wee ſhall have pleaſures for evermore, Pſal.</hi> 16.11. do we die daily? we ſhal live everlaſtingly. Saints, comfort your ſelves, <hi>Comfort one another with theſe words,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:169964:66"/>
               <head>SECT. XIII. <hi>A brief Application of the whole.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom all that hath been ſaid of the quality of our enjoyment of God, when we ſhal come to be at the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. We may learn</p>
               <p>Firſt, That not one of the Saints is perfectly bleſſed in this life, becauſe not one of them doth enjoy God, either immediately, but what we do is darkly thorow a glaſſe, by ſuch <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums</hi> as do eclipſe much of what, that <hi>Lumen gloriae,</hi> the light we ſhal have in heaven wil diſcover unto us: or ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but in conjunction with other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, which call out much of our hearts, and many <hi>Item</hi>'s of our love, which hereafter ſhal be totally ſummed up, and all laid out upon one God: or freely; but are thwarted with a thouſand impediments, which ſhal all be left behind us when we go to heaven: or fully, they are but part
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169964:67"/>of his waies that we trace him in, and how little a portion is heard of him? <hi>Job.</hi> 26.14. wee ſhal never ſee the compleatment of our happineſſe, until we go hence, and be no more ſeen.</p>
               <p>Ob. <hi>Why then do ſome perſons ſay that they are as happy, and do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy as much of God, as ever they ſhall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sol. <hi>Can I tell? perhaps it is too true in reference to ſome of them, others may bee under a temporary deluſion; but ſure I am, they bee none of the Saints, who have their portion in this life.</hi> Pſal. 17.14. [<hi>See before</hi> Sect. 2.]</p>
               <p>Ob.
<note place="margin">Saints are happy in this life.</note> 
                  <hi>But why do the Scriptures ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently call the Saints bleſſed and happy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sol. <hi>I ſhall lay before you what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of it in theſe</hi> 6 <hi>particulars.</hi> Its becauſe</p>
               <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pretio.</hi>
                  </note> The price by which we have a title to the happineſſe we have enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into, is already paid and accepted of: <hi>the poſſeſſion of God, is a purchaſed poſseſſion, Eph.</hi> 1.14. and the purchaſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:169964:67"/>is made to our uſe, upon which account our names are written in the book of life, to bee of thoſe many children whom God by the ſufferings of his ſon meant to bring unto glory, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.10. when a captives ranſom is paid, he may be ſaid to have his liberty, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his Manu-miſſion be a while delayed.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</hi>
                  </note> God hath made us a promiſe of this happineſſe before the world began to Chriſt, for us, <hi>Titus,</hi> 1.2. and ſince the world began to us in Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. to have any thing in a promiſe, is to be as ſure of it, as if we had it in ful poſſeſſion; it being as impoſſible for us to miſſe it, as it is for God to lie, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">3 <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis.</hi>
                  </note> We have the firſt fruits of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven here upon the earth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. ſomething of God drawn upon our ſouls, and ſo ſome converſe with him, and influences from him, and it was never known that ſuch as came ſo farre as to gather the firſt fruits, fel ſhort of reaping the whole harveſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">4 <hi>Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</hi>
                  </note> We are put into a capability of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:169964:68"/>this happineſſe, being (in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) made meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12. having our robes waſht and made white in the blood of the Lamb, that we may be before the Throne of God, and ſerve him day and night in his Temple, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7.14, 15.</p>
               <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">5 <hi>Spe.</hi>
                  </note> We are ſaved by hope, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24. and by whatever we are ſaved, by the ſame we are made happy, hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we ſhal rejoyce in poſſeſſion, but in this life we rejoyce in hope of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2.</p>
               <p n="6">6.
<note place="margin">6 <hi>Sen.</hi>
                  </note> The Saints have ſome taſte here of that full meal of happineſſe, which they ſhal eternally bee feaſted with hereafter, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.8. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3. and even this doth ſometimes raviſh them ſo abundantly, that they value one daies enjoyment of God, above the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of the whole world.</p>
               <p>In all theſe (and perhaps in ſome other) reſpects, the Saints are ſaid to be bleſſed and happy; though they be not perfectly and fully ſo. And we may learn</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:169964:68"/> 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi> That no nature below ours is capable of an abſolute happineſſe, as not being capable of ſuch an enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Scot. in</hi> 4 <hi>Sent. q.</hi> 8. <hi>dist.</hi> 49.</note> wee owe God very much for this benefit of our creation. I cannot tel whether it be not better then if he had made us Angels; they, 't is true, were capable of happineſſe as wel as we, and of loſing it as wel as we, but when 'tis loſt, they are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of recovering it again as wel as we, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Jud.</hi> 6. however God might have made us any of the lower creatures: look upon a houſe, a tree, a worm, a heap of dirt, and ſay, <hi>Cur non ego talis?</hi> Why had not I been ſuch? and we ſhal be worſe then ſuch, if wee enjoy not God: other creatures attain to al the happineſſe they are capable of not ſo we. And we may learn</p>
               <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">dly</hi> That they ſpeak like Atheiſts, who ſaid it is vain to ſerve God, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14. is ſuch an enjoyment of God ſo? if you be indeed chriſtians, pray be ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt and immoveable alwaies, abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the work of the Lord, for as much as ye know that your labor is not in vain in the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:169964:69"/>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:169964:69"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX (Eſpecially) To Part 1. Sect. 10. And Part 2. Sect. 2. and 10.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ſpoken in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent diſcourſe, of the enjoyment of God here by means, and of that ful ſight of him, which is offered us in the Goſpel, and obſerving how much this glorious Goſpel is undervalued, and vilified, by the ſubordination of it to natural reaſon, or ſuppoſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations; and the diſhonour that is caſt upon it by ſome other miſcariages. I ſhal here ſubjoyn a conſideration of theſe four particulars, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Whether we are bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve and reſt in no more of the Goſpel, then our reaſon will ſubſcribe to?</item>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:169964:70"/>
               <item>2. Whether we may be guided by any ſuppoſed inſpiration, or impulſe of ſpirit, that is beſide or contrary to the word of God?</item>
               <item>3. What courſes diſhonour the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; and the evil of them?</item>
               <item>4. What our behaviour ought to be towards it?</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>Whether we are bound to believe and reſt in no more of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, then our reaſon wil ſubſcribe to?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO this (having a purpoſe in each, to uſe as few words as may be) I ſhal onely offer theſe</p>
               <div type="conclusions">
                  <head>Ten Concluſions.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Concluſion,</hi> When Reaſon was in its primitive perfection, before it was purblinded by ſin: it was a very much better guid then it is now,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Concluſ.</hi> Even in that ſtate, as perfect as Reaſon was, we were not
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:169964:70"/>meerly left to the guidance of it; but a Law was added to be our directory, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. We were not left in the hands of ſingle reaſon even when it was poſſible for it not to miſ-guide us.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Concluſ.</hi> After the fall, all the reaſon that was left in the world, was not able to direct us into a way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: If it was, why did <hi>Adam</hi> hide himſelf from the preſence of the Lord God, amongſt the Trees of the Garden? <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.8.10. Yea, ſo far is a way to life for ſinners, from being diſcoverable by reaſon, that when it is diſcovered, if reaſon may be Judge, it is meer fooliſhneſs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Concluſ.</hi> Where there is the fulleſt diſcovery of God, and is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al what himſelf doth limit us unto, that muſt be our rule, and we may not meaſure how fit it is by any thing elſe. Now ſuch is the Goſpel, and Chriſt ſpeaking in it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.22.23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.9. We are not ſent to natural reaſon for orders in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Concluſ.</hi> In things where reaſon
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:169964:71"/>and the light of nature can guide us; we are yet to be guided by a ſurer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection (in caſe it be afforded us) <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them,</hi> is a
<note n="*" place="margin">Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliter notum, in agibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Dio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Carth. in Locum.</note> principle in Nature and Reaſon; yet is our obedience to it preſſed upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther account; do it, not for this is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional; but for this is the Law and the Prophets, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Concluſ.</hi> Reaſon even in men very rational is exceeding dark: Why elſe in matters of that cognizance, are wiſe and learned men ſo much divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? Truly then in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, he that wil be meerly his own Scholar, is not like to have an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble maſter.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Concluſ.</hi> What we reſt upon by faith; from the credit of God the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealer of it in the Goſpel, is more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain then what is demonſtrable by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Becauſe we conclude it from a higher and ſafer principle. Reaſon hath its evidence but from our own wiſdom: Faith hath hers from the Wiſdom of God.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Aliae ſcientiae certitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent ex naturali lumine rationis humanae que poteſt errare: theologia ex lumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne divinae ſcientiae quae deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, Aq.</hi> 1. <hi>p. q.</hi> 1. <hi>A.</hi> 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:169964:71"/> 8. <hi>Concluſ.</hi> To beleeve no more then we have reaſon for is (in a ſtrict ſence) to beleeve nothing at al. Faith is an aſſent to what God reveals, not to what reaſon dictates, and doth then looſe it ſelf when it looks for grounds in natural reaſon, without which it wil not bottom. So then if we wil beleeve nothing but what we have reaſon for, and wil indeed beleeve ſo much, we muſt beleeve that we beleeve nothing at all: for this is proved by reaſon. (See a relation of the conference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Laud</hi> and <hi>Fiſher, Edit.</hi> 1639. <hi>in folio p.</hi> 75.)</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>Concluſ.</hi> To beleeve and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe what God to that purpoſe reveals in the Goſpel, is the greateſt reaſon, becauſe the truth and certainty of it depends upon a wiſdom that can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deceive, nor be deceived: <hi>upon a light in which there is no darkneſs at al,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.5. The Lawyers ſay, that natural reaſon may be alleadged where the Law hath not determined
<note n="*" place="margin">Ratio naturalis poteſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legari ubi deficit. Lex.</note>; ſo it may where the Goſpel is ſilent; but in other caſes it muſt ſtand mute.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:169964:72"/> 10. <hi>Concluſ.</hi> To take upon us to controle the dictates of the Goſpel by, or to refuſe them upon their non-adae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quation to our reaſon: a deſign of being wiſer then the wiſdom; the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Wiſdom of God: a folly too ridiculous to have any reſidence in a ſober imagination. I hope, the fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs of God is wiſer then men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.25. In matters of Religion
<note n="*" place="margin">Non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes eſſe ſapientia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, niſi veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem. Aug.</note>, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is wiſdom, but what is truth; and nothing is truth for us to beleeve, to walk by, to ſubſcribe to, but the Word
<note n="*" place="margin">ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia eſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pida de Deo ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia.</note>. Religious wiſdom is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory knowledge of the things of God, and not to be attained by any other <hi>mediums</hi> then what God hath ordered to be written for our inſtruction, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. and if any previous diſpoſition be neceſſary to fit a man for it, it is to become a fool, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18, to deny himſelf and al his carnal wiſdom
<note n="*" place="margin">Abne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gando ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum, &amp; carnalem, ſuam ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiam. Piſcat. in locum.</note>.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:169964:72"/>
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>Whether we may be guided by any ſuppoſed inſpiration, or impulſe of ſpirit, that is beſide, or contrary to theword of God?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat I may not ſeem in the leaſt, to limit the Holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I ſhal anſwer by laying down this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</p>
               <p>In matters of Faith and practiſe, in caſe it were not the onely way, yet it is the ſafer way to be guided by the Scriptures, then by any impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſuggeſtions, or revelations with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us ſuppoſed to be from the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Of this</p>
               <p>Firſt <hi>in Hypotheſi,</hi> in caſe it were not the onely way, the contrary to which I am abundantly perſwaded of, from theſe Grounds.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:169964:73"/> 1. <hi>Ground,</hi> It ſeems to me a truth ſufficiently bottom'd upon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that the Spirit of God doth not immediately reveal any thing (in theſe latter days) beſide or above what is revealed in the Scripture. Becauſe</p>
               <p>Firſt, The Scriptures contain al things neceſſary to ſalvation, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.16, 17. If an inſpiration be for Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine or reproof, or correction, or inſtruction, or to furniſh us to any good work, al this is done by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and ſo the inſpiration is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, or beyond it: If it be for more then this, it is for more then is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. There is a curſe pronounced againſt adding any revelations or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries as of the mind of God, to thoſe that are in the Scriptures already read <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.18, 19. and note</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this book is a diſcovery of the mind of God concerning the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs and duty of his Church, cha. 1.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it is a diſcovery of what ſhal concern the Church of God from the time it was written to the end of the world, chap. 1.19.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:169964:73"/> 3. That it is a diſcovery of no more then is ſufficient; therefore he is curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that ſhal take any thing from it, Chap. 22.19.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That (together with what we have in other Scriptures, for ſo I would in each particular be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) it is a diſcovery of as much as is ſufficient and all the diſcoveries we muſt look for; and therefore is he curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that ſhal add to it
<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. &amp; Forbes in locum.</note>.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Ground,</hi> What was unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable from the Spirit of God, was not yet impoſed upon us any further then as it was confirmed by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. That the Apoſtles ſpake by in ſpiration, I ſhal take it for granted, (<hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1.11, 12.) Yet</p>
               <p n="1">1. They were wont to prove their Doctrine by Scriptures, and that you may ſee the ſweet correſpondency that is between both Teſtaments (as they are called) I ſhal ſet you down theſe inſtances</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:169964:74"/>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.24. Proved by <hi>Iſ.</hi> 52.5.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.24. Proved by <hi>Eze.</hi> 36.20.23</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. proved by <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1, 2.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.7. proved by <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.12.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9 proved by <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.7. proved by <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.10.</item>
                  <item>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.29. proved by <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.23.</item>
               </list>
               <p>That the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhould be called the Apoſtle affirms was made known to him by revelation, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.5.6. yet he proves it from <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8. And</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe that would not receive theſe inſpirations until they had exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined them by the Scriptures, are paſſed with a noble character for ſo doing, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11, 12. From theſe grounds am I convinced, that in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith and practiſe our onely way is to be guided by the Scriptures. However,</p>
               <p>Secondly. In theſe it is a ſafer way then to be led by any impulſe, ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion or revelation within us ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be from the ſpirit: which I
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:169964:74"/>am conſtrained to beleeve by theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſon,</hi> Many have pretended to revelations from the Spirit of God, when there was no ſuch thing: but the pretenders were either Impoſtors, and deceivers, or deluded by a lying ſpirit, and deceived, See 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 22.23. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13. of this we have examples of above 1500 years old,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Roſſe</hi> his View of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, <hi>ſect.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 184. <hi>Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium de vera re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. p.</hi> 58</note> and in our days, if there be two men pretending to an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate inſpiration from God, and the ſpirit that is in one be contradictory to the ſpirit that is in the other, one of them (at leaſt) is a ſpirit of deluſion: Whence a</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> We cannot ſo certainly know whether it be God that ſpeaks in us, as that it is God that ſpeakes in the Scripture, in that we may be miſtaken, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14. not ſo in this, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Galat.</hi> 1.1.11, 12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Be the Inſpiration or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe from whence it will, yet muſt the Word of God be obeyed before it.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:169964:75"/>I argue thus: That Power that is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, muſt <hi>(caeteris paribus)</hi> be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before that which is but ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: But the power of Gods Word is ſupream, and the power of Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (as ſuch) is ſubordinate to it; <hi>ergo, &amp;c.</hi> the <hi>minor</hi> propoſition onely needs proving, which the definition of a ſupream power will ſufficiently doe. Now a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Summa poteſtas eſt cujus actus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n ſubſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt.</hi> Grot. <hi>de jure belli, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>ect.</hi> 7.</note> ſupream power is that which is not queſtionable by any other juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction: But every Inſpiration is ſo far under the juriſdiction of the Word of God, as that it ought to be tryed and judged by it; for which ſee, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.2. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. And this hinteth a</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> That which proves Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be true (in caſe they be ſo) muſt needs be more certain and infallible (at leaſt) to us, than the Inſpirations themſelves. Elſe it were to prove <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notum per ignotius,</hi> a leſſe obſcurity by a greater: Or thus that which hath its evidence and certainty that it is ſuch or ſuch from it ſelf,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vera &amp; perſpicua cenſentur ea, quae non ab a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis, ſed à ſeipſis fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent.</hi> Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Juſt. Dialect. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> is more evident and certain than that which borrows
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:169964:75"/>it elſwhere; but the Scriptures (I ſpeak to ſuch as grant them to be the Word of God) have their evidence and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty (<hi>viz.</hi> that they ought to be the rule of our faith and practice) from themſelves: revelations pretended to be from the ſpirit have theirs elſwhere: [as before <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3.] therefore the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are more evident and certain, and by conſequence a ſafer guide.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> I am bound to follow the written Word of God abſolutely, whatever contradict it; not ſo Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, which in caſe they be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted by the Scriptures, I am to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them not to be from the ſpirit of God, which were not a ſpirit of truth, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.17. nor of holyneſſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30 were it contrary to it ſelf, to ſay one thing in the Scriptures, another thing in the Saints.</p>
               <p>This is my faith as to this particular; thoſe Impulſes that are indeed from the Holy Spirit of God will not; ſanctified Reaſon will not, and (by the grace of Chriſt) carnal reaſon ſhall not tempt me from ſeeing as
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169964:76"/>much of God as I can (where there is ſo full a ſight of him) in the Goſpel of his Son.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>What courſes diſhonour the Goſpel, and the evil of them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Shall not mention any thing of the language of thoſe tongues againſt the Goſpel, which have been ſet on fire of hell, and endeavour to faſten upon it a complexion as black as the mouths it drops from, leſt I ſhould teach what my deſign is to reprove nor the opinion that ſome perſons have of ſuch as eſteem the Goſpel of Chriſt, and profeſſe to beleeve and practice by it, leſt I ſhould ſeem to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe an age of very high pretences to religion and piety of ſuffering the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of both to be turned in and out. There be three waies of diſhonouring the Goſpel, which I ſhall deſire leave to complain of, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:169964:76"/> 1. When we profeſſe it, and walk anſwerable to it: when we doe ſee ſo much of God in it, and doe coppy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of God upon our hearts, and practice from it; this expoſeth it to the deriſion and contempt of the vileſt men. Have not ſome of them ſaid, <hi>Aut hoc non eſt Evangelium, aut hi non ſunt Chriſtiani,</hi> Either this is not the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel in which there is ſo much good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or theſe are not Chriſtians in whom there is none at all? Did not one wiſh, <hi>Sit anima mea cum Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phis,</hi> Let my ſoul be with the honeſt Philoſophers who were Heathen, than theſe wicked and lewd men called Chriſtians? Have not others aſcribed the upholding of our Religion all this while to the excellency of our faith
<note n="*" place="margin">Hall <hi>Chriſtian Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, l.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 118.</note>, being well aſſured that our works were ſo bad, they could never have done it. Who is it that hopes to be happy in the fruition of God, that can chuſe but make tears his meat day and night, to ſee that Goſpel reproacht, which is ſo full of this God?</p>
               <p n="2">2. When we are not only lewd and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169964:77"/>licentious, but plead allowance for it from the Goſpel, pretending the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it proclaimes to be carnal, and a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence for us to ſin, by turning the grace of God into laſciviouſneſſe, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. and expounding the deſign of it into a proviſion for the fleſh to fulfill the luſts thereof. Is it not a damnable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty thoſe men have, to be able to fetch any thing of hell out of that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel where there is ſo much of heaven? Is that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that great gulph 'twixt theſe two places removed, that they can raiſe ſuch a line of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication? This is to throw dirt in the very face of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. it is to accuſe the Goſpel of little leſſe than panderiſm to our moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred luſts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When we meaſure the exhibition of our reſpects to the Goſpel by our worldly intereſts; owning or diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truths and ordinances of it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what it is like to advantage or prejudice us in our outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſeph. Antiq. l.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> It is the manner of the <hi>Samaritanes</hi> when the Jews are in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:169964:77"/>to deny all acquaintance with them, they have no relation to any one of the Tribes; but if the Jews (as ſuch) have any beam of proſperity breaking out towards them then the <hi>Samaritanes</hi> are their neareſt Coſens, they can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive their pedigree from <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and <hi>Manaſses</hi> the Sons of <hi>Joſeph.</hi> Thoſe men no doubt have wit enough to make ſome uſe of this ſtory, who have not grace enough to make a better uſe of the Goſpel: A very fooliſh and ſottiſh ſin! Is not all that of God which is diſcovered in the Goſpel a proſpect worth the looking upon, unleſſe you can ſee the world there too? Will you not have as much of heaven as you may, leſt you ſhould not have ſo much of earth as you would? Will you have nothing to doe with God, unleſſe you can enjoy him in conjunction with other things? Pray conſider, whether the full enjoyment of God in heaven, be to be adventured upon, untill we have ſtudied, how it will ſuit our inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:169964:78"/>
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>What our behaviour ought to be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Goſpel.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis will not ſeem impertinent to the times we are fallen into (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may to the precedent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) if we have any ſence how much we doe underlive our moſt holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. Yet, this additional ſheet not being in my firſt thoughts, I ſhall be as brief as in the reſt of it, and only point at theſe Duties.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Duty:</hi> Bleſſe God for bringing you forth in Goſpel-times, when <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> was born, his Father <hi>Philip</hi> bleſſed ſuch Gods as he had, not ſo much that he had a Son, as he had him in <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> daies
<note n="*" place="margin">Diis gratias a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo, non quia na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt mihi fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ſed quod tuis tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ipſum naſci contingit.</note>; he was thankful for natural and moral diſcoveries. The Goſpel is a diſcovery of God, yea it is a viſion of him in the next degree of clearneſſe to that which we ſhall have in heaven. The bleſſing of theſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious times is ſhort of nothing elſe but
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:169964:78"/>the bleſſing of that glorious eternity. The Saints had their <hi>Hallelu-jah's</hi> for darker diſpenſations, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Duty:</hi> In all your doubts and ſcruples have recourſe to the Goſpel. Never ask what the Phariſees or Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers doe. Sure where there is moſt of God, you are like to find moſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Duty:</hi> Acquieſce and reſt in the determinations of the Goſpel. Will you appeale from God? or is there more of him any where elſe?</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Duty:</hi> Love the Goſpel. Is any thing amiable that is not here? Sure I am, if it be wiſdom, here is the wiſdom of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. Beauty, heres the face of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. the faireſt of ten thouſand, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10. Splendor, 'tis a glorious Goſpel, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. Truth, 'tis the word of truth, <hi>Eph,</hi> 1.13, Goodneſſe, 'tis the good Word of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.5. Piety, 'tis a Doctrine that is according to godlineſſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3. Power, 'tis the arm of the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.1. Peace, 'tis the Goſpel of peace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.15.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:169964:79"/> 5. <hi>Duty:</hi> Take off by your practices whatever diſparagements ſhall be caſt upon the Goſpel. Will any ſay it is not the Word of God, and ſo make it ſuch an impoſture as would cheat the whole Chriſtian world of their precious ſouls? Pray confute this blaſphemy, by giving it ſuch a power over your hearts and lives, as none but the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God can either challenge or exerciſe. Suffer it to ſway you, ſimply without any <hi>quatenus</hi> or limitation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any counter-co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand under hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Will any ſay it is not a compleat Rule for belief and practice? You muſt diſprove this ſlander, by keeping only and conſtantly to it; and by profeſſing that you doe ſo; that peace may be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you and mercy, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. becauſe it is able to make you wiſe unto ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. becauſe you may not receive any other, though an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel offer it you, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Duty:</hi> Be not aſhamed of the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. Will you be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of your God, wil you bluſh at any degree of heaven?
<note n="*" place="margin">Timor juſtae vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis, &amp; rei turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter actae.</note> Shame is a fear
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:169964:79"/>of reproof for ſome unſeemly action, and is it ſuch to own your higheſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe? It was a preamble to <hi>Peters</hi> denyal of Chriſt, that he followed him afar off, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.58. and <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> was but in the infancy of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipleſhip when he came to <hi>Jeſus</hi> by night, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. [Read 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.25, 26.]</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Duty:</hi> Hold faſt the Goſpel: Do not part with one truth, one ordinance, one duty of it. You have ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the Devils nibling away of one piece of ſome mens Religion after another, till they have no more left than <hi>Davids</hi> fool had, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Duty:</hi> Let your converſation be as becometh the Goſpel, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27. So holy, humble, harmleſſe, honeſt, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, juſt, chaſt, peaceable, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes perſons owning a Goſpel ſo full of a holy God. See <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15, 16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.10. Why elſe doe ye profeſſe it? Anſwer that <hi>Quaere</hi> of Chriſt if you can in <hi>Luke</hi> 6.46. See <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.10. The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity of thoſe that live counter to
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:169964:80"/>this Goſpel is but meerly
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui non vivit ut ipſe docuit, certum id documen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, non eſſe Chriſtianum.</hi> Juſt. Mart. <hi>ad</hi> Anton. <hi>orat, p.</hi> 128.</note> titular, that which is indeed true,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chriſtianiſmus eſt ſimilitudo Dei quantum poſſibile eſt humanae naturae.</hi> Baſil.</note> is as fair and full a draught of God upon the ſoul as it is capable of in a body of death. For a concluſion take <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8, 9.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:169964:80"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>PART. I. The Firſt Propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> The higheſt happineſs of the Saints is the enjoyment of God. This is</head>
               <list>
                  <head>1 Explained <hi>by ſhewing.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>FIrſt, What the enjoyment of God is made up of</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>1 <hi>The knowledge of God, to let in Which he opens</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 <hi>His face,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 <hi>Our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Influences from God</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Acquieſcence in God</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Converſe with God</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly, What our higheſt happineſs is</hi> viz.
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>A perfect good.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>In poſſeſsion.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Excluding every evil.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. <hi>Filling every deſire.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169964:81"/>
                  <head>2. Proved,</head>
                  <item>1. <hi>By Scripture.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>By Reaſon, all that makes us happy, is in God only being a good</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Pure,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Sufficient.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Satisfying.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Illuſtrated, <hi>by</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>3. Particulars.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt, All our happineſs here, is in what we enjoy of God here, proved by</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>God.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>The Saints.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly, Gods bleſſedneſs is in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of himſelf, Proved by</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Scriptures,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly, The greatſt miſery of the damned is, that they do not enjoy God.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>4. Improved, <hi>by way of</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Information <hi>in five Particulars,</hi> viz.
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>God is of a tranſcendent goodneſs,</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>1. <hi>In himſelf,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. <hi>To his people.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:169964:81"/>
                        <item>2. <hi>In things where there is moſt of God, there is moſt of happineſs.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>It is a falſe draught of Heaven that is not made to conſiſt in the enjoyment of God.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. <hi>Most men but pretenders to a deſire of going to Heaven,</hi> as
<list>
                              <item>1. <hi>Defying the means where God may be enjoyed.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. <hi>Trading in practiſes, where they cannot expect it.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. <hi>Who are a peoples greateſt enemies.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Reproof, <hi>of ſuch as place their happineſs in outward things, where Their</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Charracter,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Folly.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Exhortation: <hi>To labour for the enjoyment of God, where</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Motives: <hi>From the excellency,</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Of its</hi> Object, <hi>God,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Of its</hi> Act, <hi>in reſpect of Its</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>1. <hi>Kinde</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. <hi>Degree.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169964:82"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Directions, <hi>viZ.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 <hi>Increaſe your Knowledge,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 <hi>Maintain your aſsurance.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3 <hi>Abate of your love to the world.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4 <hi>Walk cloſe with God.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Declaration <hi>why we enjoy no more of God in Ordinances, either we do</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 <hi>Neglect them.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 <hi>Not ſeek God in them.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3 <hi>Not ſeek God in all of them.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4 <hi>Not ſeek after a due Order.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>PART. II. The Second Propoſition layed down.</head>
               <p>That enjoyment of God which is the Saints higheſt Happineſſe, ſhall be immediate, ſole, free, full, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>FIrſt, That it ſhall be</hi> immediate, <hi>is.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Proved, <hi>by</hi> 4 <hi>Particulars,</hi> viz.
<list>
                              <item>1 <hi>Chriſts Kingdom ſhal be delivered up.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2 <hi>All rule,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhal be put down.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <pb facs="tcp:169964:82"/>
                              <item>3 <hi>To enjoy God by</hi> means <hi>is to ſee him but in a glaſſe.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>4 <hi>Gods</hi> immediate <hi>enjoyment groaned after by the Saints.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 Applied <hi>in</hi> 3 <hi>particulars,</hi> viz.
<list>
                              <item>1 <hi>The enjoyment of God by means, far ſhort of what it ſhall be without them.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2 <hi>When the Saints ſhal be above the need of Ordinances.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>3 <hi>Death deſirable.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly, That it ſhall be</hi> Sole.
<list>
                        <item>1 Proved, <hi>in that</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>1 <hi>God ſhall be</hi> all.</item>
                              <item>2 <hi>The world ſhal be ended.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>3 <hi>Much of our</hi> enjoyment <hi>is by love.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>4 <hi>The Saints thirſt is after God</hi> Solely.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 Applied, <hi>by way of</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Firſt,</hi> Exhortation <hi>to</hi> 4 <hi>duties.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Secondly,</hi> Inſtruction <hi>in</hi> 3 <hi>things,</hi> viz.
<list>
                                    <item>1 <hi>Its impoſsible to make the Saints mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>2 <hi>The leſs we have of the world, the more we may have of happineſs.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>3 <hi>No cauſe to be troubled at the diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly, That it ſhall be</hi> Free.
<list>
                        <item>1 Proved <hi>in that</hi>
                           <pb facs="tcp:169964:83"/>
                           <list>
                              <item>1 <hi>All</hi> Enemies <hi>ſhall be ſubdued.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2 <hi>Every diſturbance of</hi> Enjoyment <hi>is an Eclipſe of</hi> happineſſe.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 Applied, <hi>for our</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Information, <hi>No Heaven where any ſin.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 Inſtruction, <hi>how to be much in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven here.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3 Comfort, <hi>In Heaven we ſhall enjoy God</hi> freely.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fourthly, That it ſhall be</hi> Full.
<list>
                        <item>1 Proved, <hi>in that</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>1 <hi>Our enjoyment here and hereafter, do but differ</hi> gradually.</item>
                              <item>2 <hi>Elſe, every evil not removed,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 Applied, <hi>To ſhew us, that</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>1 <hi>The</hi> happieſt <hi>ſight of God, out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is in the Goſpel.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2 <hi>The longings of the Saints after</hi> more <hi>of God ſhal be ſatisfied.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fifthly, That it ſhall be</hi> everlaſting.
<list>
                        <item>1 Proved, <hi>by</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>1 <hi>Scripture.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2 <hi>Reaſon, elſe.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>1 <hi>A poſibility of being</hi> miſerable.</item>
                              <item>2 <hi>Some place for fear.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:169964:83"/>
                        <item>2 Applied <hi>by way of</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>1 Exhortation, <hi>Place not</hi> happineſs <hi>in any thing that ſhall have an</hi> end.</item>
                              <item>2 Comfort, <hi>afflictions ſhort, happineſs</hi> Eternal.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The whole Applied very briefly.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 <hi>In what ſence we are ſaid to be</hi> happy <hi>in this life.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 <hi>No nature below ours, capable of</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs.</item>
                        <item>3 <hi>It is not vain to ſerve God.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:169964:84"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 5. lin. 25. for al one, read alone, p. 7. l. 3 prefix to the beginning of the l. 5. p. 10. l 7. for without r. with our. p. 17. l. 22. for frowneſſe r. frownes. p. 30. l. 12. <hi>dele</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> p. 30. l. 17. for come r. came. p. 31. l 13. for fondly r. formerly. p. 46. l. penult. adde 2.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:169964:84"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
